<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>ART CRUSH INTERNATIONAL</title>
    <link href="https://artcrushinternational.com/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://artcrushinternational.com" />
    <updated>2021-03-30T22:06:57+02:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>ART CRUSH INTERNATIONAL</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://artcrushinternational.com</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Transcription of &quot;Why Angela Hennessy Crochets with Hair&quot;</title>
        <author>
            <name>ART CRUSH INTERNATIONAL</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://artcrushinternational.com/transcription-of-why-angela-hennessy-crochets-with-hair.html"/>
        <id>https://artcrushinternational.com/transcription-of-why-angela-hennessy-crochets-with-hair.html</id>

        <updated>2021-03-30T22:02:34+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    abbreviations ah - Angela Hennessy jb - Jozefien Buydens sv - Svea&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p><strong>abbreviations</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">ah - Angela Hennessy</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">jb - Jozefien Buydens</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">sv - Svea Vikander </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">—</span></p>
<p><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">intro music</span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>jb:</strong> Welcome ART CRUSH INTERNATIONAL. I’m Jozefien Buydens</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>sv:</strong> I’m Svea Vikander </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>jb:</strong> and together we take you into the studios of artists and you can find all sorts of fantastical things in art studios like paintings and drawings and sculptures and sometimes even a coffin… And on that note, Svea, who do we have a crush on today?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>sv:</strong> today we have a crush on Angela Hennessy. Angela, I don't even know how to put it into words to tell you this story of how we met a quite lovely young woman after one of Angela's talks at Southern Exposure for her show ‘When and Where I Enter’, and this woman was lovely, but she kept talking about how much she loves Angela, how amazing Angela was and how she really wanted Angela to be her mentor. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">She was a former student of Angela's and she went to all of Angela’s events and it started to feel like a little bit, maybe this is a little bit stalker-ish or something, just maybe, you know, but it turns out that's actually an entirely appropriate response to meeting Angela Hennessy. You just become totally smitten, because she's just so eminently crush-worthy. She's a wonderful, wonderful person, she's very warm, she's very welcoming and she's a great artist.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>jb:</strong> yes! So, Angela Hennessy is a multi-media artist and her studio is in West Oakland. The topics Angela works around our mourning, grieving, blackness and the work she makes are mostly made out of human hair. So, the works at Southern Exposure that we saw were made out of synthetic and human hair and they get like this very fragile look, delicate in a way, but also very powerful </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>sv:</strong> deep </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>jb:</strong> very deep and dark </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>sv:</strong> brilliant, it’s really incredible work</span></p>
<p><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">music</span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>ah:</strong> my name is Angela Hennessy and I am an Oakland-based interdisciplinary artist</span></p>
<p><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">music</span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>sv:</strong> Jozefien picked me up and we drove to West Oakland, this is industrial Oakland but like most of Oakland it’s residential too </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I’ll do my best not to take over this interview, okay?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>jb:</strong> no! you should ask questions, you ask very insightful questions</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>sv:</strong> I know, but then it’s just me talking and that’s not the show, the show is not Svea interviewing people with the wonderful audience of Jozefien Buydens, that’s not the show</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>jb:</strong> well, I try to speak more. I tend to be…</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>sv:</strong> just kick me, kick me under the table… </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>sv:</strong> it's beautiful old houses beside beautiful old warehouses and the sounds of real work happening, real things being made, real things being shipped, real saws, real soldering irons, …</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>jb:</strong> I had to text her</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>ah:</strong> hi</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>jb &amp; sv:</strong> hello, how’s it going? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>ah:</strong> good to see you</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>jb:</strong> it’s good to see you too</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>ah:</strong> my space is upstairs</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>jb:</strong> Angela Hennessy’s studio is on the second floor of a small warehouse. It has a wall of south facing windows, brick walls, small bathroom, a sink and two large tables in the center, a rate with locks of hair.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">are they always on the table, your objects?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>ah:</strong> yeah, i tend, this is kind of how i work. I have to say I did clean up for you guys, like it was literally just one heap.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>sv:</strong> I was going to ask, are you always this organised? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>ah:</strong> this does not look organised to me at all. i tend to make lots of parts and pieces of stuff and then, depending on a particular show or some particular theme, then I sort of gather everything, but I start with like a sort of library of objects and then piece it all together. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I'm on the edge of outgrowing this space so, you know, I tend to, if I don't have things out in front of me where I can see them, then I can't keep track of them, so often what that means is that I have a lot of things out all over, but then what happens is, that gives me the opportunity when I have a specific object that I'm trying to make I have a lot of resources to turn to and to figure things out and I can always just imagine things in my head and so, I need to be able to see them side-by-side or push particular materials up against each other and actually have like a live in person experience. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">My space is pretty full and it feels, sometimes I come in here and it's totally overwhelming, it's just so, you know, even though they're all of my own things I’m like: “Oh my god, somebody clean up in here!”, but then when I start working, you know, you get busy and you just, you get in a groove. As I get closer to a show or some kind of deadline I move things around, you know, so, I like actually just moved these tables back but I had pushed them out of the way so that I could lay the rainbow down on the floor in here, you know, and then the rainbow was done…</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>sv:</strong> the actual rainbow piece is big: 15 feet wide, 8 ft tall, which is a sizable amount of crochet. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>ah:</strong> no</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>sv:</strong> and, she doesn't have any studio assistance</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>ah:</strong> I crocheted every stitch of that thing myself</span></p>
<p><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">music</span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>ah:</strong> so, this is the main table that I work at, you know, if I'm crocheting or doing hair wrapping or making flowers, I'm at this table and then I tend to lay things out, sort of as a display or, you know, that I can see what I'm doing</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>jb:</strong> it looks very cozy. It looks so welcoming and comfortable to see all these pieces laying on the table </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>ah:</strong> I mean, I like that idea of it, maybe an aesthetic of coziness makes the work seem approachable in a particular way or perhaps accessible in a particular way but then I think too that it's important that the layers of maybe discomfort or, you know, sort of some of the tensions around the work in terms of racial identities in objects that are grieving becomes another layer to the cozy, right? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">That it's all, it can all be there simultaneously and maybe sometimes as a collision, almost. And then I have, yeah, I don't know, lots of pins and sewing supplies, hair supplies, combs and brushes, things like that. I usually keep a bunch of hair to sort of hanging on the wall, so, I have the Ross Stock sort of experience what it looks like when you buy it at the store and then, I just put these two black panels up against the white wall so that I could have, you know, start thinking about my work against a black wall, which was a new aspect of the work at Southern Exposure, was having black painted walls as the background. And then over here, I guess this is like all my hardware…</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>jb:</strong> she also has a table that's all shiny metal: golden chains, sheets of copper and a very special crochet hook. Is this the one for crocheting the rainbow, this one?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>ah:</strong> yeah, this is my magic crochet hook, this is my favourite one. I have like 100 crochet hooks, but this is my favourite one</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>jb:</strong> and, it’s sparkly!</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>ah:</strong> yes, right, yeah I know. I think I'm really interested in the way that light interacts with materials and, you know, that was really like what brought me to this work, maybe in the very beginning in grad school, I was thinking about the interaction of light and so the working with the gold and working with this like glossy black enamel is very much for me, like, about, sort of calling in that visual experience that there's like a little flash of light or something that catches your eye. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">My formal training is in metal work, metal is my first material making jewellery. These are mostly all just store-bought faux gold golden chains but I, you know, in school I learned how to make chain and I used to, I thought I was going to be a jewellery designer, actually, that was kind of the path I was going in my twenties. But, I think some of that sensibility, certainly for my relationship to materials, how I work with materials now, and the kind of scale that I work at, and sometimes the little details for the fuzzy things that I do, that totally comes out of my background as a jeweller. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>sv:</strong> And, that coffin?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>ah:</strong> That, someone gave that to me.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>sv:</strong> someone saw that and thought: “Angela, Angela needs this in her studio”.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>ah:</strong> yes, that’s kind of exactly what happened. I haven’t quite figured out what to do with it, but it's just too amazing to not have. And, my son keeps on saying he wants to lay inside of it. It’s, it's actually intended to be horizontal, you know, like a coffin, so you could lay inside of the cage part</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>sv:</strong> You haven't let him yet?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>ah:</strong> He hasn’t, we haven't done it yet, but maybe we will. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>jb:</strong> Angela structures her thoughts with mind maps …</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>ah:</strong> I don’t know, maybe it's time for a new one</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>jb:</strong> There's an oversized piece of paper on the wall with visually arranged words and phrases of her thoughts and ideas </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>ah:</strong> … just becomes this place, a gathering site, you know, where it's like, I can just have random thoughts and text and language and I get ideas for titles from my maps quite a bit and things that I read. I keep note cards in my purse, I'm always writing things down so it's just another kind of form of that.</span></p>
<p><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">music</span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>sv:</strong> Instead of an artistic practice she has an aesthetic practice </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>ah:</strong> aesthetic as in a full sensory experience, a full range of experience, how I know things through my body, not just necessarily a visual experience. I’m trying to expand what that might mean. So, the hospice work and the doula work keeps me really grounded. Basically it’s, I think, if I were just talking about death and grief in the studio or in an academic environment it would be pretty easy to sort of go off in a very abstract kind of theoretical space. That, for me, is a very different way of being in the conversation, then the way that I feel when I’m, you know, sitting at the bedside of someone who is dying. It also keeps me, I think, in a fairly vulnerable space as well, you know, just understanding the precarity of being a human being.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Yeah, this idea of what textiles do for the body and with the body and the sensory experience of touch in the tactile, right, across all of that ties into death and dying and I'm really just, you know, even more broad than that, just being a human being, we basically begin our lives in textile structures or as textile structures. The umbilical cord and amniotic sac, we start that way and the first sensory experience that we have in the womb is touching, sound and it's also believed that touch and sound as well are the last senses to go when someone is dying. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I started doing a lot of research, as you do in grad school and when you have to write about your work, that really brought me into some historical grounding, looking primarily at European, specifically Victorian mourning practices, I am thinking about the role of cloth in the 1800s, that was kind of my entry point. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But I also recognised right away that this was a very white European Eurocentric practice, but looking at the hair jewellery specifically from that period and then thinking about hair as a material that in many cultures around the world is one of the materials that mediates the boundary between the living and the dead. I think you know some people maybe are more inclined to want to be present and engaged with difficult or complex topics and some people don’t, right, and so for me, I don't know how to not be, I mean, there is enough space for me to not be engaged in the politics of the black body, so. I find ways to bring, my own experience primarily, sometimes obviously thinking about the particular narrative about black female body is right now, so all of that kind of feeds into the work. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For me there isn't a space where I get to be free of that and so, I choose as an artist to go right into it. But, I think it's a different experience for people who are viewing the work and coming to it, from whatever's going on in their own lives and we are so saturated with images and information on a daily, you know, kind of constant basis and so sometimes there just isn't space till I can take on those complexities of, of identity and sexuality and danger or being, you know, with that black hole piece, like, I wanted it to pull people in but simultaneously push them away and, you know, in a particular way that, you know, is sort of a logical really, but you have to be an art viewer that is open to being moved by the work and not everybody is and that's okay.</span></p>
<p><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">music</span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>jb:</strong> Angela's connection to this works deep she's been crocheting since she was a child and hair and grieving are also deeply connected for her.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>ah:</strong> My connection between hair and grieving came out of, like, early childhood trauma and cutting my hair as a way of like marking my body and wanting to externalise grief that I was feeling, although as a child I didn't have any language like that but that was the way that it manifested.</span></p>
<p><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">music</span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>ah:</strong>  Now, it's in the seventies where everything was about the fro and so, my mom, I mean, I have specific, like, memories of my mom trying to brush my hair out, maybe somewhere near to how it is now, but at the time that was not, you know, that was not what I wanted my hair to do, you know, I wanted like the Farrah Fawcett or the Jamie Summers kind of.</span></p>
<p><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">music</span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>sv:</strong> So, you grew up in Humboldt County? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>ah:</strong> Part of the time, yes. I went kind of back and forth a bit between Monterey and Humboldt County. Yeah, my godparents had land up in Northern California, way, like, out in the, you know, they were like 60s, back-to-the-land hippies, growing marijuana and, you know, we had solar showers and a solar oven and lived, like, in a little cabin, you know. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I spent my summers sleeping outside, riding horses, and yeah, it was pretty amazing. Where we lived, up Salmon Creek Road, was, I mean, gosh it was like a good 45 minutes or an hour I think, I mean, cars were so old then, and dirt, you know, out on a dirt road. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I had a god brother, have a god brother. Yeah, there were lots of kids that lived up in Salmon Creek so, but you know we all lived maybe you know a mile to three miles apart but in the summer it was basically like whoever was the closest, they were your friends, because there was like no one else around, literally no one else around.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>jb:</strong> about the manifesto, we were thinking it was autobiographical, was it, is the manifesto… </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>ah:</strong> Is it true, was that what you mean? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>jb:</strong> yes, that’s what I mean.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>ah:</strong> yes, yes, it is. I would say the bulk of it was written maybe within the first four, five months after the shooting. I think it maybe even started out as just seven sentences and then it quickly became 10, and it was a 1 through 10, and I was thinking about the Black Panther 10-point plan and so, it started out as a 10-point plan about death and grief and wanting to bring in this idea of death as the teacher and that we’re all students in the face of death. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In terms of the show that I had last fall at Southern Exposure, you know, I think the first step maybe that that show might be taking or, you know, has taken is to sort of just make a mourning practice visible, to sort of make the connection between mourning practices and materials and bodies and spaces and light and, you know, even just taking the title of the exhibition, the ‘When and Where I Enter’ is, you know, very much about navigating different types of space and grief is certainly one of those spaces that I'm interested in. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There was a piece at the very end that I was going to make. The idea was that it would hang on the wall that had the title. I did hang a piece there that was a strand of the white kind of blond hair pompoms, so there was a piece there, but what I had envisioned for that piece was actually a lighting going to hang all the way from the ceiling and come down and be sort of a hair Globe light. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The piece that I just made for State Gallery is actually kind of that piece, so it kind of worked out perfectly that I had another show coming up to sort of immediately follow that idea. I had thought that for the closing panel discussion, I thought that I would make a standing lamp for that artist talk and that we would be having our conversation under a hair lamp and, I had been thinking about the lantern laws from the 1700s, the requirement for black people to carry lanterns if they were out at night, so this idea of lighting the black body. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">My fantasy is that I do readings, either my manifesto or have other African American, black people do readings under a lamp, sort of a lantern kind of lamp. Yeah, so, I think that’s, you know, maybe the next thing that's coming up.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>sv:</strong> When and Where I Enter was an incredible solo show and getting ready for it wasn't easy.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>ah:</strong> I got to know basically all of the hair stores in the East Bay and a few and San Francisco. But, what started happening, a couple of the colours that I was using changed so I got 2/3 of the way through the rainbow and then the third band of colours I couldn't get the colours that I needed and so, I had, I’ve had a few moments of total freak out. But, then, yeah, I just kept going back and looking for like, “Where's the old colour as opposed to this new colour?” and trying to explain to them that even though they have the same code they were different colours and trying to show these store owners these two different colours I used and they were looking at me kind of like I'm crazy. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But, yeah, I'm very particular about the colours. And actually, the third row, one colour is different than the series and the other two bands but I think it's probably not noticeable. But, yeah, it was a lot of hair, and I kept, even in the whole last week before the show and when the installation started, I kept on having to go back and buy more hair and I was having this experience, it’s, like, okay, this will be the last batch of hair that I need, like, I really have plenty and then I would turn around and be like: “Where's all that hair I bought?”, and, you know, realise that it was already in the work. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I did not sleep the night before the opening, it was crazy, I left exposure on Friday like in the early afternoon. I remember I was walking out and I was going back to Oakland to go home and take a shower and get my nails done. So, I leave the gallery and I remember turning around and I had this moment where I turned around and looked back at the show and was like: ‘Damn, that looks pretty good!’, like okay, you know, it's like that recognition of it's actually done and I left, I was getting my nails done in Oakland, literally falling asleep in the chair at the nail salon. The manicurist, she was getting all pissed off at me. She’s like: “Angela, you have to wake up!”. And, I was like: “Oh my god, you have no idea”. And then, you know, I turned around and went back.</span></p>
<p><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">music</span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><strong>sv:</strong> you can see Angela's work on her website angelahennessy.com, that’s: a n g e l a h e n n e s s y . com  </span></p>
<p><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">outro music</span></em></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Why Angela Hennessy Crochets with Hair</title>
        <author>
            <name>ART CRUSH INTERNATIONAL</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://artcrushinternational.com/why-angela-hennessy-crochets-with-hair.html"/>
        <id>https://artcrushinternational.com/why-angela-hennessy-crochets-with-hair.html</id>

        <updated>2021-03-30T22:06:57+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://artcrushinternational.com/media/posts/18/Hennessy-Black-Rainbow-2017.jpg" alt="" />
                    We find Angela Hennessy standing at a table of shiny metal objects&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://artcrushinternational.com/media/posts/18/Hennessy-Black-Rainbow-2017.jpg" alt="" />
                <p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We find Angela Hennessy standing at a table of shiny metal objects at her studio in industrial Oakland. Jozefien calls it cozy, but that’s just because she’s a real European. Nothing <em>hygge</em> about this bright warehouse space in which a lot of hair is transformed into a lot of art. Hennessy talks growing up in Humboldt County, riding horses in the summer, Blackness, being a hospice doula, and avoids telling us who gave her the genuine actual coffin standing in the middle of the room. </span></p>
<p>Angela on Instagram: <a href="https://www.instagram.com/thehouseofhennessy/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.instagram.com/thehouseofhennessy/</span></a><br>Angela's website:<a href="https://www.instagram.com/thehouseofhennessy/"></a> <a href="http://www.angelahennessy.com/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">http://www.angelahennessy.com/</span></a></p>
<p><a href="https://artcrushinternational.com/transcription-of-why-angela-hennessy-crochets-with-hair.html">Read the full transcript of Angela's interview here.</a> <a href="https://anchor.fm/art-crush-international/episodes/Why-Angela-Hennessy-Crochets-with-Hair-ets5lu"></a></p>
<div class="post__iframe"><iframe loading="lazy" width="400px" height="102px" src="https://anchor.fm/art-crush-international/embed/episodes/Why-Angela-Hennessy-Crochets-with-Hair-ets5lu" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Transcription of &quot;How Samar Hejazi Avoids Getting Stuck in a Janitor&#x27;s Closet&quot;</title>
        <author>
            <name>ART CRUSH INTERNATIONAL</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://artcrushinternational.com/transcription-of-how-samar-hejazi-avoids-getting-stuck-in-a-janitors-closet.html"/>
        <id>https://artcrushinternational.com/transcription-of-how-samar-hejazi-avoids-getting-stuck-in-a-janitors-closet.html</id>

        <updated>2021-03-30T11:28:48+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    abbreviations jb: Jozefien Buydens sv: Svea Vikander sh: Samar Hejazi __ jb:&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>abbreviations </strong></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">jb: Jozefien Buydens</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">sv: Svea Vikander</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">sh: Samar Hejazi</span></p>
<p class="p3">__</p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> Hello, hello, and welcome to Art Crush International. I'm Jozefien Buydens, a textile artist living very close to the beautiful North Sea.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Well I'm Svea Vikander, a journalist, but I thought that I lived close to the North Sea</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> Um, our coast looks over the North Sea</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Do we live on the same sea? That's so nice</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> Oh my gosh, we are connected!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> I always knew it.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> In Art Crush International, we take you into the artist studios of the world because those places are just magic.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> And we do have a website, where you can see visuals of these things because currently you are listening to a podcast through your ear drums. So if you would like to see these things with your eyeballs, go to ACI.com, where you will see some images of the work we are talking about, and also some transcriptions of our episodes. Jozefien, tell me, who do we have a crush on this week?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> This week we have a crush on a Palestinian-Canadian artist who is based in Toronto, Samar Hejazi. So Samar makes these textile works, and she also works with words. So it's textile combined with words. And she's also a sculptor and she makes these beautiful sculptures of the human figure, it's not always a complete human figure. She does something very beautiful and poetic with it. If you go to her Instagram, which is actually just her name, it's Samar, S-A-M-A-R Hejazi, H-E-J-A-Z-I, there you can see that lately she's been taking a cast of somebody's bust. And you can follow the whole process of how that goes. And it looks like a lot of work.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> It really really does. So hopefully she'll share that with us.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> Yeah I hope so too.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> So should we go to Toronto? </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb: </strong>I think we should</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Do you have your bags packed? You got your passport?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> Got it all ready.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Well we'll see. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb: </strong>We'll see what happens here.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> OK everybody, hope you've got a nice winter coat packed, because we're going to Canada..</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">[music]</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> Hi, my name is Samar Hejazi, I am an interdisciplinary artist based out of Toronto.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">[traffic sounds]</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Just walking up to the Museum of Contemporary Art in Toronto, Ontario, Canada. It's in a restored industrial building in this district where I've been staying, which is right by the train tracks and full of warehouses and stuff. Super fun. I can see old loading doors that they've preserved behind glass. Beautiful old doors, nice, strong hinges. I'm going to go in to the lobby. Hi! Are you my artist?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Samar meets me in the lobby. There are person-sized foam blocks stacked all over the place. Part of an art installation. There are workers in hard hats running back and forth and Museum-looking people in nice clothes and name tags are running around, too.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">[elevator sounds]</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> So what floor is yours on?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> fourth</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> fourth, ok. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">She takes me to an elevator that is lined with a mustard-coloured blanket. I think there's a lot of people moving in and out of here today. We step out onto a floor with an open space and large windows where an exhibit seems to be in mid-install.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> So how do you know Oliver and uh...</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> I know Oliver from U of T, like since second year of U of T.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> He went to U of T?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv: </strong>We gossip about our mutual friends as we walk up to her studio. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh: </strong>no, huh?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> No, I mean, he dressed really well.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Which, although it's in MOCA, is also part of the Akin Collective.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Is that sound, what's that sound?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Samar's space is the first on the left when you enter the Akin studio spaces. It's separated from the other studios by temporary dividers that go up about 6 feet of the maybe 14-foot ceiling</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh: </strong>So right now when you walk into my space, I have my cleaner work in the front, in these bins and the books and the papers and the desk is usually where I do the painting, and some computer stuff. Ideally I would have 2 desks, one for watercolours and 1 for computer things. Ideally I would have no computer things to do but that doesn't happen. It's 2018, so.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> About how big do you think your studio space is?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> I think it's 80 square feet, roughly? I wish it was twice this size [laughter]</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> beyond the 2 desks stands a work table with a very goopy looking silicone human bust</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> I have started working on a sculptural piece, it's a commission, based on my sculptures that I made a few years ago. So my older pieces have crystals that come out of the face or the head or whatever. So she saw a couple of those and wanted one of her own head, but with crystals coming out of her head. It relates to an experience that she had, a spiritual experience. So now I'm in the mould-making phase, so the sculpture's covered in silicone and then I'll cover this with plaster and then I'll open it up0, take out the clay, and then I'll cast it in plaster. And that's when I'll start playing around with the crystals, and breaking the piece and you know, sculpting. I did so much research to review my mold-making skills, I could write a PhD paper by the end of it. Like, "OK, go do it now, just go do it now!"</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> And you also, you had to have her come in, right?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> Yeah, she came in, we did a life cast. That was... interesting. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv: </strong>So you wouldn't wanna have to do that again.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh: </strong>My gosh, no. That poor woman. I don't know if she would do that again.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Really?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> Yeah, because she had to sit there for like 3 hours. And 3 hours with your mouth closed and your eyes closed, is fine when you have the silicone maybe, but when we started putting the plaster bandages on her head, it was heavy, you don't know what's going on, you can't talk, it's claustrophobic, you can't breathe that well, other than through your nose. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">She said that she felt like she was like a mule or a plant that was under the earth and trying to get out, or like, she was being buried, so it was pretty dark. A little dark, yeah. But she does a lot of meditation, a lot of that kind of stuff, so she was OK. So yeah, so now my studio looks like a sculpting studio. And my sewing machines are put away.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> And now that this commission has come through…</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> And now that I'm knees deep, hands deep, whatever</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv: </strong>elbows deep?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> Elbows deep</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> She's a sculptor again, and an organised one.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh: </strong>I know what I need. And so I just want what I need in front of me. And because I'm working with materials that have a curing time and I have to be calm while I'm making it, I can't be looking for a tool, or have the tool be dirty when I'm working. Just, less risk.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> I notice a sheet of paper with dozens of ordered black marks on it</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh: </strong>So I make very meditative pieces to help me connect with my body, or connect with my mind. So it'll be these repetitive marks in silence. Just line after line, small little marks in black oil stick, so they;re very dimensional. To me it's like I'm writing a letter and each mark is a word, so it's like mark mark mark, until the end of the line and then go down to the bottom and each one, even though you try to make it look like the one from before, or you're trying to keep a flow, they don't look the same and they never will. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">And I think that's part of the beauty of it. I think it just makes me...still. Like I think this is one, these are moments where magic actually starts to happen because there's no pre-plan and there's no post-. There's no show and there's no planned outcome. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> And now the real adventure starts.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Let's scout out for a place that's very quiet </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">MOCA is a big place full of heating and ventilation ducts and it's in the middle of some major renovations </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">[saw sounds]</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">We walk to the top of a 5 storey stairwell,</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Even here is quieter... </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">It is not quiet</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">[unintelligible voice on loud speakers]</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">We walk through a floor of experimental film screenings. Not quiet.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">What's behind that door?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> Let's find out. I like this risk-taking</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Me too</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">So now we find ourselves facing a bank of anonymous grey doors. I try every handle.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Eventually one of them will... dammit. Wouldn't it be funny if we were locked in?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> It'd be like "I guess we're doing it here” [laughter]</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> OK, 'Alarm Will Sound' it says over here. How is in here? This is probably the best we've had so far but I feel like we can do better.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Back out into the diegesis of experimental film and downstairs to the third floor alcove</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> ...spot downstairs</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv: </strong>Yeah? OK yeah let's try it [giggling]</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">We see one of those museum-looking people and do what we probably should have done a long time ago, which is: ask a person who might know </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh: </strong>So we're looking for a really quiet spot to record an interview</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv: </strong>Is there an office?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">But she doesn't. We have to find someone with more power.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> So do you wanna try to talk to Harshida?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv: </strong>So where is Harshida now? </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> She went down to the second floor</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> And now I really don't know what happened. Because talking to Harshida was a good and reasonable plan but... now we're opening a door, we're going down some very dusty old stairs and now we're in the basement.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> [whispering] Oh! Look at the old work here. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">There's a tiny, low-ceilinged doorless room off of the stairs, like maybe they used to store ice blocks down there or something. It's so cute and weird but... </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> Is it echoey?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> A little. Yeah. Too bad.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Now we're like running loose in the bowels of Canadian Contemporary Art, opening all the doors, seeing all the graffiti and bricks from before, when this was a factory. We find the laundry, the walk-in freezers, the old posters and tote bags. Boxes of food. everything you need to make a museum go, except for a place where an artist could be interviewed. And then, look! It's a janitor's closet. An unlocked janitor's closet.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">I mean, are you comfortable? Let me um, I'll test the audio. But let me, we can close this door.. right? </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> Yeah, I mean</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> They'll knock, right</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> We'll just apologize if we did something wrong. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv: </strong>I'm about to close the door but Samar has a better idea. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">She'll stand outside and I'll stand inside, just to make sure the door will reopen. I'm so glad that one of us is thinking. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">I'm happy to sit on the floor. Let's move this in front of you, [metal scraping]</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Despite Samar's very valiant willingness to crouch down in the middle of a janitor's closet to be interviewed, it's echoey. So, we go back to our alcove by the stairs, above ground. Looking out the window, like normal people.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">[saw sounds]</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Yeah so beautiful, we'll make good radio. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> I used to take a lot of art classes in high school but I wasn't really "allowed" to be an artist. I went to architecture school at Ryerson. I did three years of that. Realised I needed to do 7 years to graduate and be an architect-architect and I didn't love it and I didn't have a passion for it. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Dropped out and switched into new media, It's a BA of Fine Arts. But I still had the excuse of, I can be a designer or a web designer. And then by my 4th year, my thesis year, I was making installation art. And I had joined a sculpting studio. So I kind of fell into art-making and I gave in. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">And one of my profs in 3rd year, when he saw two of my projects he said, "I'm gonna ignore all the crap that you were doing all year and I'm just gonna give you an A for the year and you're gonna keep making art like this and you're going to do a year of art-making after university. And then you're gonna do your master's in fine arts and that's just what you're gonna be doing." </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">And so I guess that's when I was like, 'I guess I'm just gonna be an artist because I happen to just always fall into this, you know?' Yeah so I graduated, I didn't end up doing my master's like he told me to. I started doing sculpture and that work was based on my relationship with the spiritual world. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">And then after that I wanted to do work that was more cultural. I think most of my work is about layers of identity and how I relate to those layers of identity. Originally, I am Palestinian. My grandmother runs a Palestinian heritage centre in Jordan. So we always had embroidery around us, traditional embroidery and very traditional things, always. Women's crafts and stuff like that. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">So I started to do embroidery. Just to try to connect. And I did an instructional residency in Mexico and then I went to Berlin for three months for another residency, to develop the concept a little further. And then I went to Palestine and Jordan and then after that I started working with textiles. So, floating textiles and traditional embroidery practices and trying to push them into contemporary art.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv: </strong>What does your grandmother think of your art practice?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh: </strong>She loves it. A lot of it is a little confusing. But a lot of it she just gets. She gets me.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Ah, is she an artist?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> No. No. Maybe. Like, she has taste but I don't think she's ever explored the idea of being an artist. That just wasn't an option. She's more entrepreneurial as opposed to businessy, and I think my work is very conceptual. So for a lot of them it's like, "Why did you do that? It's so nice without you doing that." I have a piece, I did the embroidery and then I cut the embroidery so it's like fluffy and to them it's ruined. But to me it symbolises the abstraction of tradition. And it talks about how now culture and tradition is being used as a way to lure people in, as a novelty, for tourism. But the truth of the traditions and the cultures and the rituals aren't explored as deeply as they used to be. So it's just an abstraction of what these things used to be. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">[music]</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh: </strong>I think people like to make up stories about my work. Your experience of my work is your experience. But I think what they get wrong is when I say I'm Palestinian or I'm Canadian and you know, emigrated, and they always think that there's a sense of victimhood. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">And it's like, No it's not, I'm privileged, like, I wasn't kicked out, we came on our own. I'm not a refugee. I'm just telling a story of who I am. I think sharing what is is harder than sharing a story that is already embedded with so much drama. I'm trying to stay pure to my narrative. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">I make jokes when people give me ideas of what to make in my art. I'm like, "I'm gonna start a group chat with you guys and you can just list all your ideas on that chat and then when I have a creative block, I'll check in, but until then…"</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> That's a great idea! Have you done that yet?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> No I haven't. but it's like that would be an art piece in and of itself. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">[music]</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> In terms of your studio space, can you talk about how long you've been at Akin and how long it's been?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> I've been with Akin for four years. Akin is an organisation that provides studio spaces for artists. So it becomes a collective of artists working side by side. And obviously that in turn becomes a community of artists. Akin facilitates that but also has different events that they organise for us, and for others. And show-and-tells and just lots of opportunities to flourish as an artist. I love Akin. I think Akin is a great community. Like they really take care of their artists. When you get evicted, they'll find another place for all of us to stay together. They understand the importance. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> And so, did Akin ask you to do this residency? Or did you apply?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh: </strong>I applied. There was a proposal.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> What did you pitch in your proposal?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh: </strong>I was just telling them what I was working on. I was working on an installation piece that, again, was about identity. So I sewed onto a fabric that dissolves and I dissolved it at the studio and all the things that I sewed held together because they were connected. And so it's floating. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">I hung it from the ceiling. And there's no fabric holding the threads, so it's just the threads.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> And is that the one you did with some text? Like, a song?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> So it's a song called “Homeland", it's a Palestinian song, and now it's the Iraqi anthem and it's about loss of land and all of that. And my grandmother used to sing it to us. So I wrote it out in this English-Arabic. When Arabs that are living in the West communicate with Arabs in the East, they'll use the Latin alphabet. So for the sounds that the English alphabet doesn't have, we'll use numbers to make the sound.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> And is this because the script is hard to learn?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> I think it just kind of happened in the '90s with ICQ and MSM Messenger, when all those platforms came up. And not all the keyboards had an Arabic option and everything was in English but we were still trying to speak in Arabic sometimes. And so, I thought that was a pretty amazing phenomenon. And I was surprised, nobody talks about it! I mean, even the Arabs don't talk about it. It's part of an identity that forms.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">[music]</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> So what do you like about the studio space?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> I like the professionalism of the artists around me. Everybody who's at these studios is serious about their career. They show up and they think deeply about what they're doing. And they're committed and they dream big. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Yeah, I think it's important who you have around. It's such a crazy career to go into. I don't know what next month is gonna look like, both financially and creatively. But you just kind of have to have this faith and a commitment to yourself and...</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> So how does having these other professional artists around, how does that help you?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> There isn't as much helplessness or hopelessness. Being around other people that are achieving, it kind of gives you hope.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> So if you could change one thing about your studio at Akin, what would that be?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> I wish my space was more square. My work is three dimensional now so it would be nice to walk around my pieces and have my pedestal in the middle. I think I would like to have a second wall instead of the curtain wall that we found to delineate me and Eva. But we can't drill into the floor so that;'s why we couldn't put up walls. And I wish I had a window. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">But whatever, once I start working I don't think about it. It's usually in between. I would love to have a clean section for the painting and then a sculpting section and a little couch for embroidery...</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> In your day-to-day life, do you have another way of supporting yourself?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> I teach art to kids on the weekend. And that's all.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> And has the government of Canada given you any funding? </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> Yes, I just got a grant from the Canadian government. And I got an exhibition assistance grant from the TO arts council. So, yeah, they help. It's great. One of the biggest benefits of being here. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">[music]</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sh:</strong> You can see my work at www.samarhejazi.com. Or on Instagram, at samarhejazi.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> That was so much fun to have you guys with me there in Toronto. Jozefien, um, did you not make it? </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> No, I guess there was something wrong with my…luggage.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Did you go to Hawaii instead of Canada?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb: </strong>I think I did. It was just too cold for me.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv: </strong>I see, so that's why I'm frostbitten and you have a tan. Excellent, perfect, good. So what do we have on next for the show today?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb: </strong>It's the beautiful online thing! I found a beautiful website which is called beleefdenachtwacht.nl</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> [laughter] “beleef de nachtwacht?”</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> You say that beautifully Svea. So translated in English this means 'Experience the Nightwatch' and this is a very famous painting by the Dutch painter Rembrandt.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">[see the BOT at www.beleefdenachtwacht.nl]</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> And our crush next week is Angela Hennessy</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv: </strong>Ugh I love her and I love visiting her studio, too.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> Yes me too. She is a wonderful artist who works with hair and death and blackness. You can see her work at houseofhennessy on Instagram.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> And that's our show for the day. Remember to subscribe and give us a review if you like us </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> And if you would like to hear more of us in some personal letters that get into your inbox, subscribe to our newsletter on our website, artcrushinternational.com</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> We would love to join you in your inbox</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">[laughter]</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> Great</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Bye! Thanks for listening, bye bye bye.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Transcription of &quot;When David Wilson&#x27;s Garage got Real Bloody&quot;</title>
        <author>
            <name>ART CRUSH INTERNATIONAL</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://artcrushinternational.com/transcription-of-when-david-wilsons-garage-got-real-bloody.html"/>
        <id>https://artcrushinternational.com/transcription-of-when-david-wilsons-garage-got-real-bloody.html</id>

        <updated>2021-03-22T15:44:13+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    abbreviations jb: Jozefien Buydens sv: Svea Vikander vo: Voice Over (Svea or&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p><em><strong>abbreviations</strong></em></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> Jozefien Buydens</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Svea Vikander</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>vo: </strong>Voice Over (Svea or Jozefien) </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> David Wilson </span></p>
<p class="p2">__</p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb: </strong>This week we have a crush on David Wilson</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb: </strong>But DW is a very talented artist and he makes works that are aesthetically pleasing, socially pleasing, and mail-pleasing too</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Male pleasing? Tell me more about this male pleasure component. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> Mm, so this male pleasure component, and this might be disappointing, is a postal mail</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> ahhh</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb: </strong>pleasure component</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv: </strong>Yeah yeah yeah, I knew that, yup </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> So, David Wilson you can write him a letter and he'll write you a letter back </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> That's amazing, I love that. So did you send him a letter yet?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> Uh, no I didn't </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Oh</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb: </strong>But I think you did, right? Because you got mail from David Wilson </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Oh, I did get mail from DW but I never sent him a letter, he just sends me things.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb: </strong>OMG you lucky woman</span><span class="s2">. </span><span class="s1">[laughter]</span> <span class="s1">So this is very postal mail pleasing, I would say</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Yes, definitely, that's definitely what I would call it </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> It's like a party in your mailbox!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Shall we, let's take them. Let's go</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> Yup, it's exciting</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> I'm glad you're excited. Let's gooo</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> My name is David Wilson and I'm an artist and I live in Oakland, California, and I like to draw and I like to organise things</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> So Jozefien picked me up, and I was not available because I was on a call, because I had completely forgotten this interview, and so I'm actually wearing my pyjamas</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> Oooh, nice!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> That's my pyjamas [giggling] but at least I'm wearing a bra. Top notch, Svea!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb: </strong>Top notch, you are so on top of it</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"> </span><span class="s1"><strong>vo: </strong>We pull up to David's house </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> It's going great, it's going great, I appreciate it. </span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>vo:</strong> It's a single family home on a tree lined street. Also, the BART tracks are very close by. </span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Did he say 'go to the front door'? </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> Uhh, there was nothing as like that in the mail</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>vo:</strong> We walk up the front stairs but </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Cuz I hear, like, kids in here</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>vo:</strong> We decide not to ring the doorbell cuz it sounds like there's kids inside </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> Oh really? Huh.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Is there a path to the back? </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> Well, on the other side I thought...</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv: </strong>Maybe we should try that before we disturb a family</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> Before we ring the doorbell</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>vo:</strong> We push open the unlocked wooden gate and step inside</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> OK, let's hope we don't get shot, this is America. OH MY GOD LOOK AT THIS BOUGAINVILLEA, IT'S SO GORGEOUS</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> Svea gets really excited about a huge bougainvillea plant that's growing up the side of the house and hanging down over a large handcrafted wooden table</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> *shimmer noise* I love bougainvillea and if you do too you should follow this strange little IG account called for_the_love_of_boug. *shimmer noise*</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> This whole thing with the table... Hi! How are you? Sorry we're late</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> Oh, no worries </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv: </strong>Beautiful place</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> Welcome</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> Hi! </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> Nice to see you again </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>vo:</strong> We meet David, who is standing in his immaculate art space. It's not quite a studio because he does most of his artwork outside so this is a place for carefully storing artwork. For thinking about things, for designing things. Organising things.</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> It's very nice. It's a beautiful art studio</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> And since I work outside primarily, I wanted to be able to have the kind of space that would be more for looking at art since making work tends to happen outside so not needing it to be, basically the function is to look at things.</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> There's a lot of beautifully framed drawings of natural items, landscapes, the great outdoors. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> It was formerly a garage, back when cars were small, and it was built in, I think, 1916, same year as our house. And when we first moved in, again, this was leaky, the floor would flood, it just was a very rough space. We are now kind of after a year of me chipping away at renovating the space we're in now, a clean and art-safe kind of space. So the floor is concrete and was recently re-poured and kind of has that freshness to it. The ceiling was a little exercise, where I used the wood that I use to make frames and basically used strips, this was about a 10 hour project of standing in front of a table saw, which did of course end up in an emergency room visit.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Did it? Really?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> It did, yeah it did, yeah,</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> And of course, Svea wants to hear more about that.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> What happened?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> Well, of course, when I got to the point where I had safely felt like I had milled enough of this material to do this ceiling, I thought <i>I don't wanna have to realise I've come up short</i>,<i> so let me do just even more</i>. And that was, my eyes were glazed over, and I just reached in, just touched the saw blade as it was spinning. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Do you have a scar?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> Well it's amazing, the body, it's a very subtle scar on the tip of my thumb... I reached in</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv: </strong>Where, it's horizontal?</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> Yeah it's kind of just across the tip there—</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Wow, hardly at all.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> I just reached in there and just zip, right across there, and so of course there is one piece in here that's got a little bloodstain on it.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Where is it?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> Ummm</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> And of course, Svea wants to find that bloodied piece on the ceiling</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> The actual piece is on the side of the house, but there's a little drop... </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> This is the literal sweat and blood of the artist</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> Well you can see some of the saw marks there, I think it was in one these ones...</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> How many stitches?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> It was actually the glue. They went for the glue. But anyway I'm whole and the room, you know, has that little extra ju-ju. But yeah it's a wood ceiling, strips of old growth douglas fir.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">And yeah, you're pointing at my cassette player, which is probably my twelfth one of those, if not more, I have a real relationship with that particular model, it's a, you know, battery powered, it has a built in microphone, a really nice condenser microphone, so it tends to make everything sound good if you're recording outside. Which I tend to do, with a lot of the kind of gathering projects that I do. So yeah there's a chunk of wood serving as a stand, also a storage solution.</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Cool</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> Yeah, got some tapes in the works</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Do you listen to music when you're working?</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> Yeah I do, I really like listening to music</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> What are you listening to now? </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> Let's see right now, I think it's uh...My dentist growing up as a child, he was a very awkward Vietnam vet who didn't have much of an ease of rapport with his younger kids, who he worked on. His son was a bootleg tape guy at a flea market and offered them as a way of connecting with the kids in his practice.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">But I was, in the end, really the only kid who was taking him up on it. So every time I went to his place he would just let me go wild in, like, the bootleg tape room of the dentist office. So this is the Talking Heads live, this is from the Stop Making Sense Tour so yeah, live in Milwaukee, ‘84. So this is how I got a lot of music actually. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> What are these here?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> This was a gift from my friend Kelly Best, who is a woodworker in the Bay Area. He's an aesthete in his own very rough, natural way. I forget which tool store this is from, it might be from Hida tool down in North Berkeley but yeah, I've since worked with him and a few others.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Paul Discoe, who is kind of like an OG woodworker in West Oakland, who was part of the first wave of the San Francisco Zen Centre coming to the Bay Area, and was sent by Suzuki Roshi, the teacher, to go to Japan to learn temple carpentry in the 70s. He lived there for a few years. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">He's just a real resource in this pre-industrial Japanese style carpentry and I've worked with him and a group of people on a couple of projects, but one more involved five year long house building project; so yeah, this is a chisel I am holding, you can see I have not taken the best care of it. There's chips and things in the front, which Paul would not be happy with, but the first phase of that class was basically learning to sharpen your chisel on a stone, a wet stone, which I missed actually, I was working on a project when I arrived. </span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> So you never learned it</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> I never like learned the proper technique. I'm always like, am I doing it right? Well also, I'm a little, I'm a little neglectful and lazy, but that's ok.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>vo: </strong>David shows us his catalogue of invitations.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> I made this box and started putting this together...</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>vo: </strong>Paper archived in a hand-made wooden box—and they are literally invitations, to music events, art events, community events. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> I like how it came out. So It's basically a photocopied, um, little guide to what's in this box with these miniatures. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> What was the FaceBook thing you did?</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>vo:</strong> David was the first artist in residence at FaceBook and he invited the employees to hang out on the salt flats near their offices. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>vo:</strong> He also made them return the invitation in a wooden box if they wanted a print of one of his salt flat drawings.</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> And then having these incidental little conversations with their neighbours of like, "Oh, I meant to do that, do you have any extra?" And being like—</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>vo: </strong>And if they didn't do it..? He didn't give it to them</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> 'Oh no sorry, that was kind of a point, wanting to have that kind of commitment to each other,' you know that kind of little, teaching them a lesson.</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> They're like ‘WHAT?!’</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> Yeah!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> ‘The artist, not at my service??’</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> Yeah, so it was kind of cool, I had a good experience.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Do you do any artwork outside here?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> At my house?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Yeah</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> I'll draw outside but mostly it's by design an incentive to kind of walk, </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> To go onsite</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> But I can show you something which is kind of cool.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb: </strong>It's the coolest thing ever</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> No way! You have an outdoor shower?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> And, uh, an outdoor toilet [flushes toilet]</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>vo:</strong> An outdoor shower. In Oakland.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> What's this handle from?</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> The handle was sent to me by my friend who lives in Cape Cod who I spent a lot of time with growing up</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv: </strong>That's amazing</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"> </span><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> I want one… Right now.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> But do you shower out here? </span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> Yeah, this is where I shower and often go to the bathroom</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Oh, you're toilet paper is all soggy in the rain</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> Yeah, I have to start...</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>vo: </strong>We head back inside and look for our best potential audio.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Wait, does that come out?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> We can roll it out, yeah...</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> OK, how flexible are you?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"> </span><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> In terms of,</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Like would you be </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> Like, physically flexible?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>vo:</strong> It's probably the big low table on which David was showing us the invitations he'd made over the years. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> Yeah yeah yeah, you know, I'm...</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Would you be able to sit underneath that table?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> Sure</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> With us?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> We can get under there.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>vo: </strong>I crawl in first and David offers me a cushion</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Oh, well, there's only one</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> I can sit on this</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> But what's Jozefien gonna sit on? </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> Oh... </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>vo:</strong> Then Jozefien begins to pass me the equipment</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> This one is for us..?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> Yeah, one of them, like, one of them</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Do these tripods go any lower? Is this as low as they can go?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> Is it too high?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Yeah, this is, uh...</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>vo:</strong> And I grab at the mics blindly because I can move my arms but not my head</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Yeah, I mean, it'll probably be OK</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>vo: </strong>David crawls in opposite us</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> OK, I'll sit down, and do more of a recline I think</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Yeah you can, but we need you to be close to this guy</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> Is this close enough?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> No</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> No? How close?</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb: </strong>With the small wooden box Svea has manoeuvred into a mic table between us. I'm too tall to sit up entirely so I kind of lean up against Svea's legs. [laughter] Very cozy.</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">[Musical interlude]</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> I grew up in Massachusets and I'm an East coast person, so basically hung out in that area for most of my life. I went to school at Wesleyan University in Connecticut so that's also right in the pocket there, so uh, studied art amongst other things there, religion and philosophy and cultural studies, and moved pretty directly into a focus on drawing, coming from a few years in the painting department.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">And that was also a shift for me back into what felt like the inspiration and agency of exploration. I kind of always thought about that moment as kind of an important one, just to kind of think about what way you work as the central question in art making, and finding the way to work that enables you to be the way that feels right and the way you wanna kind of engage the world. </span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">So moving out of the studio was very liberating, as well as finding material, such as drawing, that was very portable that just kind of became my counterpoint to movement, moving through this town and getting to know it really deeply. So I spent my final year there kind of making a series of, you know, surveying drawings. I always thought of it as kind of encouraging good habits in terms of mental health too, in terms of engaging walking, and engaging that time, and then I'd also had a background in music. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">So planning shows was a part of my early childhood and you know, high school time, growing up in suburban places where there weren't necessarily—if you want to play music for your friends you would do it in someone's house. So that home-based house show self-organising instinct was always a pretty natural thing; and just being a social person, that kind of translated into another side of my work that's evolved as kind of a community based organising practice. So I organise a lot of things and they tend to intersect out in the spaces I find when I'm drawing. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Moving to California when I was 23, I was kind of taken by that intersection and proximity between the city and the open space, so my time drawing again was just a perfect kind of counterpoint to get to know this new area and to take it in through the lines and then share it through the organising so, bringing people together in these different spaces that I had gotten to know while drawing.</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> Was there a specific reason why you moved to the Bay Area, or why you chose the Bay Area? </span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> Well, it was incidental in some ways but a friend had spent time growing up—she grew up in Chicago but had family out here, so she'd kind of been exposed to this place—and was excited to try and rally a crew of friends to move together. And you know, this was in 2005, so the idea of getting a warehouse space in West Oakland and having a spot to land and you know, get into things and all that was very tangible and real. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">I'd never been really out of New England and wanted to see what was going on out here and thought at least I would come visit my friends who were living here and get a sense for what this place was. So I visited and some friends lived very close by here, in Berkeley, and we, you know, we cruised the Berkeley hills, went for that loop in Stinson, up the hill, up Mount Tam, that kind of open space experience, and went to see a show at Lo Bot at the time, which was a warehouse in West Oakland and kind of got a feel for...it felt like a very porous art community and that there was that spirit of self organising was very clear to me immediately.</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">I had never really experienced a place where you could move into both, like a powerful nature experience and then this powerful community experience within a day, I was like going back and forth. So that kind of blew my mind and it just felt natural. I just could imagine myself here.</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">The period where I was working at a bakery, I was doing these early morning bakery routes, I would start at 5am and initially I didn't know the area at all so it would take me you know, a couple hours to get through it all. Eventually as I got to know the area and just got to know my route faster and faster, I could go faster and faster and end up with an hour to basically have on my own. So during those little bakery delivery hours I explored found all these different spots that have since been touchstones for various projects and drawing ideas.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">And then I kind of proposed organising something there with those friends I was playing music with, and just put together a little evening event and people used a map that we made and came together to hang out and listen to some music. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">It was quite a special evening and then turned into a little bit like a seasonal outdoor music series. That particular form lasted about a year or so, or year or two, and then those friends, Daniella and Frank, moved away. I kind of continued on with that and just also, in organising projects that are bringing people together you also are exposing yourself, and getting into all kinds of new conversations and collaborations, and so my ideas moved into broader territories than just music. </span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">It became food collaborations and ideas of building space or kind of creating more of an installation to support the gathering, and more just turning into these kind of open experiences, as opposed to just performance. So that just became its own little series of things that happened from 2006-2010 or so and then I also started getting a little more support from various institutions and things. I started to kind of do more institutional collaborations and it has evolved what that is, but always a strong instinct to get people together.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> Is that something that you had to deal with a lot, when you were doing these gatherings, like with like police complaining, neighbours complaining, </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv: </strong>This is America</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> Yeah, which is interesting, and a lot of the designs for organising this kind of came from this funny "what can you get away with" mentality, and it's almost like since there's not like a space that's readily being offered, you have to kind of take it. Even if the taking is kind of a very gentle taking of it, like singing a song with some people (it's not like a hard effect on a space), still you're compromising some rules. So yeah, there was definitely occasions when we would encounter some authority.</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Are you cognisant of the privilege that it requires to do this kind of work?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> As space becomes more of a challenge for everyone—having had enough privilege like you said, to even think that you're able to do something, to be able to navigate a police conversation safely, is—is a privilege.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"> </span><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> Where does 'ribbons' come from?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> The name specifically came from a conversation with my friend Frank in a very 24-year old, 25-year-old instinct to name things, it's like ‘a project should have a name’ kind of conversation, so the word 'ribbons', if I'm being honest, came from a conversation about farts, about how we like, </span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">[fart-like machine sound]</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> Is that my phone? That was my phone!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> An apt timing!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv: </strong>So wait, how does ribbons and farts...</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>dw:</strong> So it's again, kind of embarrassing, kind of just what it is, but basically we were having a conversation about how we visualise farts and my friend was saying he had like a cloud kind of metaphor and I was like, well, it's like ribbons, when you walk, like a trail, you can walk around...we kind of joked about that. Anyway, we quickly let go of that first reference point but that, if I have to be honest, is how that name came. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">But I found that it's a very nice name because it’s a name that allows for multiple associations, especially gathering projects or organising projects that are inherently collaborative, leaving it open to all kinds of people. I think there's something nice about the idea of being wrapped in ribbon, even if, hopefully it's not a fart ribbon. I hope that's not the effect.</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">[musical interlude]</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">OK, to see some examples of these events, look at www.davidwilsonandribbons.com </span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Wow, welcome back from David Wilson's studio in Oakland. That was so amazing.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> That shower in the garden? I want that.</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> I know, I know, you said that! Maybe he'll let us visit and shower, maybe that can be part of his art project. HEY DAVID WILSON ART PROJECT IDEA let other people shower in your shower. Social practice, woot woot!</span><span class="s1"> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> woot woot!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Everybody loves social practice. [laughter] What do we have next on the show for today?</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Transcription of &quot;Why Simon Tran Paints in His Bedroom&quot;</title>
        <author>
            <name>ART CRUSH INTERNATIONAL</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://artcrushinternational.com/transcription-of-why-simon-tran-paints-in-his-bedroom.html"/>
        <id>https://artcrushinternational.com/transcription-of-why-simon-tran-paints-in-his-bedroom.html</id>

        <updated>2021-03-22T14:34:31+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    abbreviations cl - Craig Langdon jb - Jozefien Buydens st - Simon&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>abbreviations</i> </strong></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">cl - Craig Langdon</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">jb - Jozefien Buydens</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">st - Simon Tran</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">sv - Svea Vikander</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">—</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><i>intro music</i></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Good morning everyone and welcome to ART CRUSH on this beautiful Monday morning. My name is Jozefien Buydens.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: My name is Svea Vikander.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: And, in ART CRUSH we take you into artist studios around the world, because artist studios are wonderful places to be in. So, Svea, tell me, who do we have a crush on today?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Today we have a crush on Simon Tran. Simon Tran is also known as ghost ghost teeth and if you open your app called Instagram and look up ghost ghost teeth you will find his account and many quite beautiful, very detailed abstract or abstracted India ink and acrylic paintings.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: That sounds exciting!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: So, Simon Tran invited into his house and outside workspace in North Berkeley.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Let's go and visit Simon Tran.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Let's go!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><i>music</i> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: I’m Simon Tran, I’m a painter, my work is all like: “psssshhhhh” and stuff, that's kind of awkward, right?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: I like that! </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><i>music</i></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: I first interviewed Simon Tran for the radio in 2015 for Arts in Review with Gregory Sharpen. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Not this one, but the next one. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">We listen to the interview as Jozefien drove us to Simon’s house.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: Hello hello!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Hey!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Hi!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: How’s it going? </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Good. How are you?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: Good to see you. Do you need a hand or…? </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: I’m ok. I can’t really give you a hello hug ‘cause I’m carrying this box… Hey, how are you?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: Good, good. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: This is Jozefien.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Hi! </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: Jozefien. Simon. Nice to meet you.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Simon, nice to meet you. Thank you for having us. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: It’s really cramped, it’s mostly just a bed in there, but…</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Simon welcomed us into his old Berkley house and showed us to his bedroom, which also doubles as his studio. It's brightly painted with his paintings covering most of the walls.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: … I can’t really have too many people come by.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: He shares it with his partner, who also seems to share his aesthetic. Bright colours, retro themes, lots of records. You know, like, the room of a cool person. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: This is my room / studio, so, I keep all my paints under the bed, here. I share this with my partner Kari Simonsen, who’s a painter as well and, so, we just collect like colours, so, yeah, that's all over there, got the record player over here. Part of my record collection is here, the other half is at my my parents’ garage, ‘cause there's obviously no space here to kind of store stuff, so, I've been kind of forced to, to put a lot of it in storage. My partner and I like to collect video games, it's a big, it's a nerdy thing and that's one of the anxieties that I had of you folks coming into my room, is seeing, like, how much time and investment I put into, like, collecting video games. I…</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: That’s cool!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: Shut up! I mean, like, but yeah…</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: She’s European, they don’t even have those kind of things over there.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: You don’t have TV’s! That’s what I’ve heard.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><i>laughing</i> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: But, my daughter plays video games and I encourage her playing, to play video games ‘cause that was something that I was encouraged to do when I was a kid and parenthood is all about what your parents will let you do, so, you let your kids do and you vicariously live through that, but, I don't live vicariously through my daughter, because we both play video games together, so, it’s fine. She does sports with her mom and all that stuff and she plays video games with me and that's how we bond, over Kirby which is like a character. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Do you want to show us outside? </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: Down the stairs here. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Susan…</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Simon lives with two older Berkeley artists, Craig Langdon and Susan Brooks, who are tinkerers and inventors and creators of electronic music.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: It's just nice to be able to grow up with my Berkeley parents, basically. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: The house is vibrant coloured, kind of labyrinthine.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">It’s awesome, and, your house is beautiful, I love it. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">We came across Craig who was also building his own synthesizer, steaming milk at a very fancy looking espresso machine.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: So, how would you describe the your work that you're doing, your pedals, and…?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>cl</i></strong>: Oh, electronic music?! </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: The house is decorated with Simon's own mural like paintings. There’s one on the front door and one on the outside back wall. The house is also situated directly on top of a creek. Simon told us that it was Strawberry Creek, but according to my fact-checking, which is also my husband, it’s Cordonices Creek. The creek runs through a tunnel underneath the house and Simon often works outside. He took us for a tour of his backyard, which is hundreds of feet of creekside, huge eucalyptus trees and a small bridge, reserved exclusively for the deer.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: Yeah.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: This is amazing! </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: I know, it's really great.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Do they own this place?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: Yeah, they own this house. It’s been, I mean, it’s very influential on the work as well just like a representing that kind of fluidity of the stream, you know, in the work there's a lot of movement that I try to work with.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: You work on this table?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: Yeah. I put on a tarp and then put on, stretch canvas over it and then I start pouring paints and then like playing around with it back here. A lot of times, like, seeds and bugs get into the paint and I'll just paint that into the, the composition there. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><i>music</i></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: So, of course we record the interview in Simon’s very lovely and very small bedroom and it’s a really tight squeeze, because we have two chairs, three mic’s, one laptop and two TV dinner tables in the say three feet between his bed and his closet. Simon sits at the foot of his bed, but first he brings us some really, really good coffee. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Thank you! </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Oh, this is so good, thank you! And, it’s so tasty. That’s when you have when you live in a small space…</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: This is so efficiently! There all these efficient furniture pieces.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: In a way and in another way it’s just crazy, because everything is just…</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: In terms of your current art practice, how long have you been working out of your bedroom?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: laughing. You say it as if it is, like: “Okay, Simon, like, you work out of your bedroom?!” </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: No, I work out of my bedroom too. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: Oh, OK, cool, so we’re good, we’re good. Yeah, and you're here in my bedroom right now.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: It’s also, It’s also, I work in your bedroom. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: It may be close to like 10 years, I’m just like: “Okay, this is what I’m gonna try to do”. Previous to that I was working as, like, a commercial actor, I did a lot of improv, like stage improv and I think the spontaneity in the work comes from being an improvisor.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">I feel like ‘improvisor; is kind of a dirty word, comedians, improvisors in general are just like, just like: “Turn it off, man! Save it for the stage, let’s not do this in the grocery store where you have to make fun of everything”, and, you know, but that's inside of me, I've been doing that for years and my friends are horrible people, that are improvisers, they're horrible people, they're horrible people, you know. They think they’re funny, but, they just, they just, you know, gotten to the point where they tell jokes so much that it's just poo-poo and kaka that makes them laugh. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">I feel like my work is about mistakes and covering up your mistakes. A lot of these organic shapes that I paint is because I've made some sort of mistake behind it and then I'm layering on top of that, but then that becomes the thing, so maybe purposely making mistakes, which I think my my ex-wife would probably, like, say: “That's true. It's like you're just making mistakes and making things harder for yourself”, but there's a certain density to it that I think represents labor. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">I come from a working class family, my dad was a tool grinder machinist and my mom worked in preschools as a preschool teacher and being born here in California and raised in California and raised to be an American but also being a Vietnamese person, I can say it was hard, but it was definitely something I had a lot of questions about growing up. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">I didn’t really have a lot of Vietnamese friends outside of family and I didn't speak Vietnamese, my parents were kind of learning English as I was learning English, so, I think it just kinda English stuck more. So, there's this kind of detachment that I, I have to Vietnamese culture. I think I'm trying to regain part of that or like research that more, not like on a daily basis, but it's just something that's on my mind and I think I try to interpret that and process that in my work as well. You know, nostalgia. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">I think my work has a lot to do with nostalgia in a lot of ways, like, the colour palette references things from my past and also, things of, like, a youthful nature perhaps, like, video games and animation, anime, manga, and…<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>My grandparents used to live in the backroom of my parents house or there was like a separate room and the walls was this ugly teal colour and I just, it was just too much for me at the time, but now it's just like, every time I see that colour, which has become like a favourite colour of mine, it reminds me of my grandparents, so, it's things like that that I'm really drawn to with colour and I like how we associate memory with that, with colour, so, yeah, that's a large part of the process for me, kind of reacquainting myself with these lost colours.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><i>music</i></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: I wanted to ask you about your school experience. Was that a good one or not? </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: Being from Long Beach and moving to, like, basically Daly City, you know, where San Francisco State is and being around all this grey that's over there, it was really depressing! And, like, I missed my parents and my family and my friends down in Long Beach, so, I moved back and I just went to City College for too long and I met my ex-wife at San Francisco State and she's from San Mateo, so, she moved down to Long Beach to live with me and we got married. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">I felt like I got, I was a little self destructive. My uncle passed away and, yeah, he took his own life and it was just like one of those things where it’s just like, why, you go before your time, and there's a lot to process there and just trying to understand and my relationship wound up suffering. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">I felt like having a kid would be one of those things where, just, like, I wanted to celebrate life versus mourning it, but, you realise mourning is part of life and you have to just go through it, and…<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>So, we wound up having a divorce, like, a year after my daughter was born and that was a really hard time. It’s taken a long time to kind of get through that.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><i>music</i></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: My daughter's 8 now. When I'm around her, like, I feel like I'm invincible and you know, so, it’s, she wound up being, I mean, she's a blessing of course and she's a good kid. She’s very considerate, she doesn't eat her vegetables but, you know, that's fine. I wish she’d listen to more, like, punk rock and stuff but she doesn’t, she doesn’t. But, she's cool, she's cool, she's very eccentric with her outfits and such and, like, I said, she's very considerate, so. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">So, after the divorce I, I was just like, I need to do something different with my life, I need some direction, so, I decided to, you know, apply to school and I've always wanted to go to UC Berkeley and it was, like, the only school I applied to and I was, like, if I get back in, if I get into the school, I'll go back to school, and it might be weird, I'll be like the old man on campus, I wasn't the only old man, so, that wound up working out okay. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">The faculty were really cool, you know, they were closer in age to me than the kids and what was funny was, like, some of the students, which I befriended, later said that I was, like, too cool for school, in the back of the class kind of thing, which I thought was very flattering to feed my ego: “Yeah, I am cool, I am cool”. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">But, I did really well, like, I went back for, like, art practice and I was just, like, this is what I want to do, I just want to paint, I'm going to make work, I’m gonna figure out what all this stuff is all about and, like, have some sort of conversation with people that want to figure things out as well and it was a great community of people students and faculty alike. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">UC Berkeley is a fantastic school, I can't gush about it enough, and I did really when I went back. I graduated and I had my daughter with me, so, she walked with me during the art practice ceremony and that was a great achievement and I felt like: Ookay, now I have some direction”. And then, fast forward to now, working at Berkeley High School and I'm just like: “Ah, this is weird”.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><i>music</i></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: I’m working as an instructional assistant in the special ed department. When they're doing what they need to do and they don't need me to be their cheerleader, I can just kind of kick back and draw and I'm working on a couple of drawing classes as well. So, I draw with the kids and I feel like that's modelling correct behaviour.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Totally! When you were at UC Berkeley, where did you do your painting? </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: I was fortunate enough to get into the honors program there and they have studios that are in Wurster, so, all those like architecture kids that dress all black and really think they're too cool for school and they’re, but really they're just making these diagrams out of styrofoam, you know.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Yeah, I know. Styrofoam is like the least cool material.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Yeah. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: Right?! That’s not sustainable, you know. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: That material is like… like, playdough is cooler than styrofoam. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: Yeah, right. It comes in different colours and it's easier to work with. I mean, I was just, like, jealous of those architecture kids and architecture in general, ‘cause, like, you know, you take part in building buildings, you know, large things that was just something that I've always been…</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: So, you’ve had a studio in Wurster?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: Yeah. It was subdivided between six other artists I think, I think it was like 6 other people, and we kind of shared that space. It was nice to see other people working and, like, picking up on their studio practices. I took full advantage of that and I was working, like, day in and day out, it's like all the freaking time, and just made a bunch of work and at the end of my stay at Berkeley, like, I made friends with gallery owners of the Compound Gallery and invited them to come to check out my work in the studio and they agreed to that and they came and I gave them candy and…</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: You bribed them with candy? That’s amazing!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: That's what you got to do, kids. You got to have your Jolly Ranchers and your Dum Dums, if you don't got that you don't got no career to look forward to. Look at me, I’m like, I'm living a life, having an interview in my bedroom, working at Berkeley High School. Yeah, I made it. So, if you want to make it you got to get on that, that sweet tooth.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: What’s your relationship like with Compound Gallery?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: They’ve been really good to me. They’ve been showing my work, they gave me a solo show shortly after I graduated. I showed a lot of the work that I was doing in the honors program and I think what they were attracted to perhaps was just, my focus on working and making work and just like, okay, I'm just gonna, I want to make work, I’m always going to be making work, so, hopefully we can establish some relationship together, which we have, I mean, I’ve been working with them<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>exclusively in the Bay Area for the last couple of years basically and I'm happy with that. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">These works on paper are gonna be shown along with some other paintings and, and sculptural kind of pieces, sculptural paintings, I guess. And that’s, like, that piece over there…</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Yeah, I was looking that.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: …which I titled ‘Dumb Architecture,’ which is basically me being jealous of those architecture kids, right. I’m just like trying to, like, I’m really bad at making a straight line or making right angles, which are essential in a lot of design, so. I think a part of my process is, like, okay, I'll try to make something and it's obviously not coming out, so, I have to cover it up with an organic shape.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: So, you’re just kind of a failed modernist.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: Yeah.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: You’re just trying to paint this straight, simple lines and, then it, like, it doesn’t work, so. Okay, here’s this, like, very labour intensive, like, abstracted pattern, like, you know, here’s my hallucinating…</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: Yeah, here's my mistakes, which is also reflective of, like, the times too, right. It was just, like, there's a lot of mistakes going on in our government, the very transparent, and I think my work kind of reflects times as well. I see a lot of art that's being made right now that's just like really loosey-goosey, and, you know, wavy and, like, people just making these absurd things and creating these figures that are just like, it's weird, you know. What are you doing? My kid could do that, you know. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">And, and it's just like an interesting time for art making, we're just like, yeah, we’re reacting to all this crazy stuff that's going on, which is basically just art making in general, like, the history of art has always just been a reflection of the times, I guess. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: If you could change anything about your working space what would you change? </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: Make it smaller! I don’t know, I think, maybe, having more space. I mean, I’m adapted to it, just like, I make sure I don't drop or spill any paint, you know, which helps you create a certain kind of shape and a certain line and that you have certain painting techniques to reflect being meticulous in a way, right. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Yeah, I was wondering how that works, working out of your bedroom. Do you sit on your bad while you paint and draw or do you stand?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: Yeah, you would think it would be more comfortable sitting in bed and painting, but oftentimes, like, I'm hunched over and the brushes are working well and I'm making these lines and I'm concentrating on that and I'm kind of just, like, really kind of focused and not… </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Sometimes it's not comfortable, but there's a certain intimacy with the work that I have, you know, you literally wake up and you look at the wall and it's something that you're working on and you see these mistakes you need to paint over and it's just like: “Ugh, back to work”, you know, but it’s, it's also kind of this living thing in a way, but I would like to work, like, on a larger scale and just, like, have that kind of, be, at the ready… </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Sometimes it's a chore to go outside, I’m having the back yard and it’s cold, like, today it’s super windy, I am not going to go back there, but, yes, I guess just more space is always… But then, you know, do you want to be that person where you’re just like: “I just need to make bigger and bigger paintings”, and be that, a person that just really has to do that, I don't know.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: And as we’re wrapping up, Jozefien’s putting away the mic’s and the cables, I realise that there's one thing that I have to do. It’s not a nice thing, but it has to be done. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><i>singing.</i> Hello, my name is Simon and I like to draw, draw rings. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: Yeah, what’s good is that, like, none of the high school kids know that, that reference, so that never comes up, thankfully, yeah yeah yeah.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: But it did when you were in high school?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>st</i></strong>: Well, I wasn’t like … yeah, it did. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><i>music</i></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: You can find Simon Tran’s work if you go to www.ghostghostteeth.com</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><i>music</i></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Thank you for joining us to Simon Tran’s very special art environment. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: That was fun! </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">[Our Beautiful Online Thing of the week is “With Love from Nowhere” by <a href="https://www.ellieniblock.co.uk/">Ellie Niblock</a> and <a href="http://atarabzouni.com/">Alaa Tarazbouni </a>. <a href="https://www.withlove-nowhere.com/"><span class="s2">https://www.withlove-nowhere.com/</span></a>.]</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Next episode, we have a crush on our friend Tramline de Senna, who is from California but lives in Belgium and makes sculpture that is so lush and gorgeous and kind of disturbing.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: That sounds great!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Find her on Instagram at tramainedesenna for more information. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: I’m really looking forward to seeing her space. My name is Jozefien Buydens.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: I’m Svea Vikander. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: If you enjoy this show and the artist we interview, please consider telling a friend about it or leaving a review on iTunes</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Or, falling in love with the artist yourself.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Indeed.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb &amp; sv</i>:</strong> Bye!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><i>outro music</i></span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Transcription of &quot;Where Elle Sofe Sara Goes to Refuel&quot;</title>
        <author>
            <name>ART CRUSH INTERNATIONAL</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://artcrushinternational.com/transcription-of-where-elle-sofe-sara-goes-to-refuel.html"/>
        <id>https://artcrushinternational.com/transcription-of-where-elle-sofe-sara-goes-to-refuel.html</id>

        <updated>2021-03-22T14:14:50+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    abbreviations jb - Jozefien Buydens ess - Elle Sofe Sara sv -&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>abbreviations</i> </strong></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">jb - Jozefien Buydens</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">ess - Elle Sofe Sara</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">sv - Svea Vikander</span></p>
<p class="p2">__</p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> We’re going to this place near the town I live in. It’s called “Avzi” but the way that it’s spelled is (spell), so when I first moved here, I thought it was pronounced, “Av-zee.” So yeah, it’s a very small town on a river.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Elle Sofe Sara says that she’ll pick me up and drive me there. I get on my snow pants and parka, snacking on some Swedish knackerbrod while I wait for her. [snow pants zip sound].<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>I get a call from Elle Sofe, and she says she’s at my house but I look out the window and I don’t see her.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">where, where are you? did I give her the wrong directions?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Then she pulls up and I hop in.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Because you see, it turns out that I hadn’t given her the wrong directions—I had moved. This person, whom I had never met, knows where I lived until just a few months ago. There’s no other Canadians in this town. We’re the only ones. And everyone just kind of knows where everyone else lives. Normally, I think that makes things more convenient. Just not this time.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">[car driving sounds]</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> We chat awkwardly as we make our way up the other side of the valley. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> I grew up here</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> In Avzi</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> In Avzi. In that blue house.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> oh really?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> yes</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> does your family still live there?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> it's, my sister and her husband have bought it so they live there. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> oh, ok</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> my parents live in the other house next door.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> so nice.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">She wanted to build a house here but that she couldn’t afford to, so she and her husband bought a house closer to town. It’s so expensive to build things here. You can only dig into the ground a few months of the year, and those are the months in which mosquitos and no-see-ums descend upon the earth like a plague. But there are no mosquitoes now, as we park and get out of the car. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">[getting out of car sound] Everything is white. Elle Sofe directs me toward a side road winding through a sparse, birch forest. We’re walking uphill and the wind is blowing. So if you hear us breathing heavily and sniffing our running noses, that’s why. It’s actually pretty warm today, uh, about minus 9 degrees celsius. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> but I was thinking a little about, eh, the art studio. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> yeah</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> yeah because that's the concept of this podcast. I was thinking about it and I think that I'm not that attached to a house, or a certain house. I'm more attached to places. I use the places —or the spaces that are available in this area or in other areas. I can just bring my stuff to a place, I have more of this nomadic thought, perhaps, in how I work, in that I don't need one sudio that I use all the time. I work sometimes here and sometimes there. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> And do you think that's connected to being Sámi? Or is that just you personally having adapted. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> Uh, I'm not sure. I think it, I mean it's connected to the Sámi very clearly. For me.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> yeah</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> Because we are just kind of borrowing a place for the time being. Not using it more than we need, and I kind of take it in that</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> that's exactly what you do, right?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> I take in that in how I create.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> can you describe where we are? What you see?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> Well we see, we are coming back to Avzi, the place where I grew up. And here it's a small village, with about 70 people living here. And when I grew up, there were like two families mainly, so it's like, my family or my relatives and then there's the other, the Haetta family kind of, so.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> I ask Elle Sofe if this is still true today.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> The families are more further apart, but we are still, I'm related to half of the village, yeah. But of course the other half have been my neighbours. Where you build a house is still affected by families living there. So, I wouldn't build a house in Heamogieddi or other small villages outside Guovdageaidnu, because if I don't have a connection there.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> You just wouldn't feel comfortable, or..?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> Well, it's not, I don't know. It—how would I say it? I wouldn't, I don't know, I don't feel that it would be my place to build a house.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> This path in particular is one that Elle Sofe walked as a child.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> And also now, when I have moved back, it has been like a place where I, I go, to, yeah, just to meet myself in the nature. Yeah, this path is a, it's a road. To a water called Vuorasjávri, and it's a nice fishing water near where I have grown up. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">And I feel that more and more, in the later years I also need a place where I can be filled, to refuel. And this is kind of a place that, and I also kind of discovered that working as an artist you are very much developing stuff all the time and, like, giving very much. That half of the work is also kind of the refueling. Yeah, so it's not just producing new things, new art, new films, new performances. But refueling part, maybe it's 50% and it's as important as the production. Because the refueling also gives to the artwork. So I have been more focused on that the last year. I really take conscious decisions to make those times for myself. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">And now we're going up hill, in this small road, to V-javri, yeah we will soon see the water. But it's frozen now. [laughter] And yesterday I saw reindeers, yes, they were crossing the water. And so I called my cousin and he's like, "Oh, really, are they there already?" and then he drove up to put them the right way. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> So they were going the wrong direction? </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> he came here on his snowmobile to get them back to the herd. Because this other side is another reindeer herding district.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv: </strong>She gestures to a 30-foot wide section of frozen river with an island in the middle of it.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">As we walk further, Elle Sofe explains to me that her cousin herds reindeer using a snowmobile. When we approach the lake (which is also frozen), I notice snowmobile tracks in the snow. She says they’re probably his. They’re not the only tracks in the snow.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> these are rabbit tracks. You see two, two small. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> yeah, it's like a little leap. OK, I have to take a picture. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">We haven’t seen a single other person the whole time. It is so peaceful out here. It's like what you imagine when you do a guided visualization. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">I love it when there's this frost on the branches and you can see each branch individually.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Having reached the lake, we turn around and begin to walk back.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess: </strong>Of course when I was younger I used to dream about having a bigger studio. At the same time, I see now that I have a space in DaidaDallu and I have sometimes a space in the theatre and some other locations in GDG and that works well as well. And I have sometimes the cycle that I am with the reindeers in October and parts of April.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> what happens in April?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess: </strong>In April we are moving the reindeer from this place, in Guovdageaidnu, to the coast, in Skaidi. So it's also a migration with the reindeer where my husband and the other herders need help from others. Yeah, because there's, the reindeer need to be herded 24/7.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv: </strong>Don't they naturally want to go? I thought they liked the coast.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> Yeah, they want to go. So it's not we, who are moving the reindeer, the reindeer, they go themselves, and we follow.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> OK and just make sure everything's ok?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> Yeah, because reindeer, they go where they find food. So if there is, the snow has melted more on this side but there is another herd there, then we have to prevent them from going there and mixing with another herd. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> I ask Elle Sofe if she gets ideas for her work when she’s out walking, or herding reindeer. She says no.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess: </strong>I think they actually come when I'm in motion. I think they come when I am traveling, like when I am here, I don't notice the rabbit tracks or snowmobile tracks, they are very common, so. It's maybe when I meet other cultures or perspectives that I see more my own perspectives. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">I have also got inspired by saying or poems. This new work, 'The Answer is Land' is also a poem by three Sámi artists.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv: </strong>She very carefully explains to me the way that this works but I don't think that I quite understand. You can find a link to the poem in the show notes. And then we're back to the car. I search for a Kleenex to wipe my dripping faucet of a nose.<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>Elle Sofe offers me some toilet paper. They don’t really do Kleenex here. But everyone has a roll of toilet paper in their car.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">*music*</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> Well I just kind of started out with films and theatre in school when I was 14 years old. That was so much fun for me because I wasn't really a good student at school. I found it very, not so much fun. [laughter] And so when we could do theatre and films at school, I found my path and I found, Wow, this is so much fun and, this I can do. So from there I just decided that I want to go to this gymnasium that has this theatre and dance and I want to learn more.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> and the Gymnasium here is a high school, or, how old were you when you went to gymnasium?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> 16 years old. 16 to 18 you go to gymnasium and I moved to another town. First Alta, which is about 2 hours away, and then to Tromsø, which is about 6 hours away so, yeah.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> that's pretty young, to make a move that far.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> Yeah, it is I guess but in this village we didn't have those genres so I had to do it. And I found it really, I really liked it and it was really worth it for me.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> what kind of projects were you working on, when you were 16?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> Hmmm well, I was just kind of getting to know what it's all about and just actually dancing very much. Like modern and ballet and hip-hop and all sort of genres, just to dance and to get familiar with what it's all about. But I also started out with my own choreographies to Sámi music or to joik, and that was with me from the start. And I remember that I used to perform in small events or something and then get calls from the college or university and could I come and perform, and when I was just very young and made a choreography or joik to some Sámi music and that's kind of the start. It just took more and more time so I got very involved in everything. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> So, being Sámi, how did you feel that your family felt about your desire to become an artist, dancer, filmmaker? How did they feel about it?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> Well, my closest family, like my parents, they were very supportive. I think that's also, they have been very supportuve to all of us, also my brother and sister, because we have all gone to very different paths. My brother is a carpenter and my sister is a teacher and I am an artist, so we have gone different paths. I think that our parents have always been very supportive and when I moved to London when I was 19, they said, "OK, you can do it, we can support you. But we have no idea what awaits you there and how we can help you to manage this. But we support you and you can do it."</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> That's so sweet.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess: </strong>Yeah. It's maybe sometimes when we are at DaidaDallu, with the Sami artist collective, we all kind of have that in common. My generation of new Sami artists, we don;'t have any, like, our parents or grandparents who are being artists or anything in that category. They don’t know anything so we don't have any grown-ups we can ask about that stuff.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv</strong>: That's so interesting. Can you explain why that is, that nobody has a parent or grandparent who was an artist?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> I mean, there have been some Sámi artists in the beginning of 1900s but not so many. Like, in my family on my mother's side, here in this area, they were reindeer herders and they moved with the reindeer from this area to the coast. Like we also do today. But at that time they worked both the mother and the father worked full time with that. And the kids went to school but in the beginning the reindeer herding kids had school in the summer months, or, connected to the cycles of how they move with the reindeer. So it's just been very other culture and focus. And it's maybe, how can you say, maybe like after WWII, after 1950s that the Sámi community in this area had more modernization or institutions, that people started to work also outside the family.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> So, if you were a creative person early in the 1900s, and you were herding reindeer, you would find a way to be creative in that, in your tasks in life, I guess, right? I mean, there were, there are Sámi arts, there is joik and duodji, I'm sure there are other ways to be an artist that aren't just, like, you and I being professional artists, it's not the only way to be a creative person, right?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess</strong>: Of course, I maybe said it a little bit wrong. Of course there are also artists. Like, in my family. There are great handicrafters or great joikers or great poets, in a way? How they can tell stories or how they can also have words in the joiks or tell about something in a certain way that is very poetic. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Can you mention a little bit about language, I think some of our listeners won't know about Sámi, or that there are six living Sámi languages, can you talk about why they're stressed, or threatened? </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> Yeah, Sámi languages, there are originally 10 Sámi languages and I speak Northern Sámi, which is the biggest language, there are about 20,000 people who speak it, so it's not a lot. And the Sámi languages, are one of those that have undergone this Norwegianization process, or Swedenization, it was forbidden to speak in schools like when my parents grew up. So it's not that long time ago, my parents remember that they couldn't speak Sámi and they learned Norwegian in school, in the boarder schools. And so Sámi language has been through rough times and now Sámi is an official language in Norway but of course there is a lack of books and material to learn it. And also, children's series and children's books and everything. So, me and my husband, we both speak Sámi fluently but we also see that Norwegian is a big, that our kids also get very influenced by Norwegian or English. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv: </strong>So, getting back to you and your time in London. What was that like? You went from Tromso to London, what was that like?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> That was very, like, really big change. That was a huge contrast to what I was used to. And also, both, I just started dancing when I was 17, the dance techniques, so I was new to dancing and also this kind of living in the city and yeah, everything that comes with that. So, it was, I was really exhausted the first time. Like, the first months. There's so much sound, also, in London. It's never quiet. So I was really exhausted but at the same time I really loved the school, I loved to learn something new that was completely new to me.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> What school were you at?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> Laban Trinity, it's a contemporary dance school, which is based on Rudolf Von Laban's theories about space and time. So it has both the focus on dance technique but also choreography. So that's maybe why the school was a good place for me.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> In what sense? What about that made it a good place for you?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> Well, I think I knew from the start that I want to create my own work, that I don't want to dance in someone's work, that that doesn't give me as much as to create something from zero. And also because I felt that there is, there is a lack of that expression that I like to see on stage and I would like to create. So I wanted to, I knew that I wanted to create my own stuff. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> And when you say that there's a lack of expression you'd like to see, what kind of expressions are you bringing to the stage, now?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> Mmm, now I am working on a new performance called "___Eana", 'The Answer is Earth' and there I am working with joik, traditional S song, and I am choregraphing the audience, the audience is participating in the work, with seven performers, joikers and dancers. And what I'm trying to kind of do there is to give this experience to be part of something. Part of a community or part of a traditional song. To be there, experiencing it with the body. And I don't know if I have seen that kind of work other places, but it's kind of this, how—how, I'm, interested in how we can take Sámi perspectives or views, also on dramaturgy and time, how I can shape that in an artwork. In a performance for example. That I don't just use linear story, but that I can in some way make the audience experience things in a different way. To experience the ground that we are on, that we share. Or experience time in a different way. That's kind of my nerdy stuff that I feel that there is a lot of potential, not just to do theatre in Sámi language and that's Sámi theatre, but that you actually look, at what can a theatre be, what can a performance be, in a more whole sense.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> are you making work for Sámi people, for non-Sámi people, for both?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> I'm making work for everybody. I think my work is from a Sámi perspective but it is universal as well. It has, I think it's for everybody. I don't think that if it should be only for Sámi or only for, I think that's, I don't think about that. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> What is that like, being an artist mom?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> That has been a big shift in my artist life. Because I was 30 when I had my first child. And until that point, since I was 16, I had been just focused on dance and working wherever people asked me to come. But when I became a mom I became more rooted also in this village. So I had to kind of shift a little bit. And at first I just kind of took every job that I got. Also in theatre, choreography, films, stuff like that, and also administration work for the Sámi artist collective. But two years ago I took a decision that this is too exhausting to do so much different things. That I took a choice and I said, "OK now I'm going to focus on these two projects and that's it."</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv</strong>: And the two projects are "The Land is the Answer" and...</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> The other project is a feature film. Called "Arru". That means...'hindring', I'm not sure about your Norwegian. I'm not sure about the English word. I'm sorry. But I think that's also maybe a work in progress title. So I am quite sure that it will change. It's those two projects that I'm working on and yeah, it's very exciting. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">*music*</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> This <i>ribadit </i>tradition, it's something, when I worked with a performance a few years ago I interviewed elderly Sámi about dancing. And that was not something that the elderly knew about. They'd say, "I don't know anything about dancing, we didn't used to dance." </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">But then when I asked them more about how they moved when they were young, in the parties, or other places, then they described this tradition. Which I kind of have then, which I see as dancing in a way. it's not formalized dance, certain steps or something like that. But it's maybe more that it just occurs in that moment.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> it's ritualized in some way. When Sámi people in the past were doing this movement together, it had a meaning...the movement's not accidental, it has meaning to it.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> So that's why I call it a tradition as well. Because most people knew what it was, or had seen it before. So it's not just something one or two people did, but it seems like when I then decided to make this film, I wanted to know a little bit more about it, I spoke to elderly people about it</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv</strong>: so what were the movements?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> Well they were holding the belt, because there is a belt on the midje</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> On the middle?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> On the middle. Both men and women have it and you can hold the belt from behind and you can hold it sideways or turn in certain ways and it's not, it doesn't seem when I have talked with people that it's anything formalized, you just do it the way you want. And also very important, in relation to how much space there was in the place. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Because back then the houses were much smaller, also the houses where they had wedding parties. So it's not that much space, like, in today we have weddings in the sports hall, which is quite big. So there's much more space on the floor. But tradition was that the guys could pull a girl in the belt at wedding parties. You could hold them in the belt and kind of walk around or turn around, that's how I got it described.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> And what did that signify?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> That was kind of, if you were a little bit interested in that girl, that would be a way to approach. So that's how I understood it, and...there's also stories where the guy's mother also comes to hold the girl in the belt. Because the mother is then agreeing that this is a good match. I think its very funny. I mean, if I, I think I would be so embarrassed if I was like 20 years old and my mother came to help me to [laughter]</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> So it was only men who would hold women's belts? And someone told me that sometimes there would be a tugging and sometimes the belt would break? This seems kind of, like, gáktis are really special. And expensive. Like, your gákti belt, I would be really angry if I had a gákti and I had a belt and some guys broke it. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess: </strong>Yeah, I mean, there are many different stories of how it ends. It doesn't always break. Or the girl can also take it away, like to open it. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> She would unbuckle, or untie her belt? And then walk away? What did that mean?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> Well I think then she would be like "Ugh, screw you guys, I'm not part of this."</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv: </strong>So would that be signalling that she did not want to get married to that guy or wahtever. And then he has to give her belt back? that's very humiliating.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> Yeah I think so. [someone] also told me that she went to get her belt from a guy and in the end there was an aunt who helped her with that or something like that.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv: </strong>Wow, so this guy took her belt home? Jerk.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> Yeah but she got it back. And she also described parties in the 1960s, like in a wedding, that all generations are there at the same place. So there are also this, she's describing there are security guards, elderly women standing around in the hall, watching everything and being security guards. And if anyone, if it gets too much trouble, they will go and intervene. And fix things. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv: </strong>What if a young couple was really getting along, would they also intervene? If they were dancing too close or spending too much time together? [laughter]</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess;</strong> I don't know.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> I'm sure they would do something.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> I don't know if young people would do that in front of elders. Maybe that would happen somewhere else. We are very, like this 'intime' zone is further away among Sámis. We don't talk that much about love or these kind of feelings. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Why do you think that is?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> I don't know. I think that is something that we should talk more about. Like intimate feelings or sexuality, or I don't know. It's more like, I never talked about that with many people.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> Your work addresses some of these themes, right?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> I think that working with dance it naturally comes up. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> So um, let's talk about your studio space. Which for today was the great outdoors. Can you tell me, what do you like about it?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> I like that it gives me calm and gives me also energy. Yeah, and it's something that I can't control. It has its own mind.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> What's good about that? </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> I don't know what it exactly gives me. But there is something about being outdoors that connects me back to reality in a way. And it also, if I am stressed about developing these new projects, then I can kind of connect to the outdoor, or to nature, or to the ground, "OK, I am just a small piece in the bigger picture." </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Its not, sometimes working with, or as an artist, can become very egocentric, also. Your artistic voice, your blah blah blah. I get a little sick of it or also myself, to investigate all the time. I really like to be in different environments, to get perspective that OK, I'm just a small person in this world. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv:</strong> it's nice not to feel like the centre of the universe. It's nice not to feel like that. So the other question we ask is what you would change about your space. What would you change about your beautiful outdoors?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> About change...That's a hard question, Svea. But like, if we, the outdoors is not the only space I work in. I work in different places. I would like, it would be really nice to have a real dance studio here in this place. Where every time I come to a real dance studio I just like, Ahhh, the floor is warm, there is dance mats, there's speakers that have good sound... I really want to have such a place sometime, where I could work sometimes.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv: </strong>Do you ever think about climate change, or global warming? I was thinking maybe you would change that, I don't know. It's a big issue up here, in Sápmi, and for reindeer herders in particular.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>ess:</strong> That is a big issue. But it's also one of these things that is, it's very huge. A huge issue so I have to kind of also, sometimes kind of protect myself in a way that I don't feel bad about it every day. Even though it affects, especially the reindeer herding future. Which is also the future of my kids. But I have to maybe think a little bit, what I can do to reverse it and to change climate change. But I also have to be present and look at the beauty which is now. Many things in Sámi society are very difficult. There are many, many social issues or many political issues, that are there all the time. And they are pressing, in our culture and language. Which can be very hard if you really get into it and experience it every day. I have to be aware of it but also to appreciate the nice things that we have. </span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Transcription of &quot;Why Mariam el-Quessny is Finally Calling Herself an Artist&quot;</title>
        <author>
            <name>ART CRUSH INTERNATIONAL</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://artcrushinternational.com/transcription-of-why-mariam-el-quessny-is-finally-calling-herself-an-artist.html"/>
        <id>https://artcrushinternational.com/transcription-of-why-mariam-el-quessny-is-finally-calling-herself-an-artist.html</id>

        <updated>2021-03-22T16:26:33+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    abbreviations jb - Jozefien Buydens mq - Mariam El Quessny sv -&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>abbreviations</i> </strong></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">jb - Jozefien Buydens</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">mq - Mariam El Quessny</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">sv - Svea Vikander</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">—</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><i>intro music</i></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: I have missed you so, so much. Welcome back everybody! This is ART CRUSH INTERNATIONAL. I’m Svea Vikander.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: I'm Jozefien Buydens.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: And together we take you into the artist studios of the world.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: We have lots of news. We're launching a podcast! </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Ooooo</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Celebration time, come on!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: That’s not how it goes, that’s not how it goes. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: No?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: No.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Celebration time, come on…</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: No. “Celebrate good times, come on! Celebrate, have a good time, come on!”</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Oh, really?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Celebration, let’s celebrate, it’s all right. All right, this is really long…</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Wow, yeah, yeah. I made my own version.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Anyway. So, podcast is really exciting. Very keen for you to look up the show on iTunes or wherever you get your podcast, subscribe, listen, review, rate, tell your friends, tell your pets, tell your plans.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Write us emails.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Write us emails, well, that’s good too. Our email address is contact@artcrushinternational.com.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: And, we’ll respond, ASAP.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: We didn’t do a good job with that last time, but we’ll do much better this season. Jozefien, who do we have a crush on this week?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: This week we have a crush on the Egyptian artist, who lives in Oakland, Mariam Quessny. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Tell me more</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: So, Mariam moved from Egypt to Oakland a few years ago. Besides being an artist, she's a </span><span class="s1">mom of two small children. And, Mariam makes these beautiful drawings about motherhood. Exciting, right.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Yeah.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: They're absolutely beautiful. If you want to go ahead and develop your crush on Mariam, you can follow her on Instagram, so her name is Mariam Quessny, and she goes by stay_at_home_artist. I think we should just go ahead and see what Mariam has to tell us.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Right. I wish we got to Cairo, but she lives in Oakland now, so let’s head over to Oakland.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Yeah. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Okay, let’s go!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Let’s go. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><i>music</i></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: I am Mariam Quessny. I call myself an artist now, semi confidently. I’m helping mothers celebrate their story through art.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><i>music</i></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Mariam Quessny lives in an apartment complex in the Grand Lake neighbourhood of Oakland with her husband and their two small children.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: We were early when we left to get to Mariam’s apartment. We actually got there early, but parking was nowhere to be found, our parking Gods having abandoned us. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">They could look back and apologise or something. Right?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">And then we got stuck behind a delivery van.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">We’re being patient, but you still apologise for blocking the freakin’ road. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Hi, man!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Hi, man! I want your apology. I’m not mad, but I want an apology.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: We ended up circling her neighbourhood for 15 minutes before parking at the bottom of a very </span><span class="s1">high hill.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Anyway, we can walk. We’re European.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: We’re Europeans, we walk.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Europeans, we walk. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: That sounds good. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: If we had gone directly to Mariam’s apartment, we would have been almost on time, but, we had a Google Maps problem.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">You know what, we’ve, we've actually missed our…</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Oh, really?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Yeah. I walked us too far in the wrong direction.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Ooo, look at this! </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: We did stumble upon a pay-what-you-can farm stand under the freeway though. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Feral Heart Farms, certified organic! Pay what you can, you just put the money in the little lock box.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Because this, is Oakland!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: This is so cute. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">We walk up a steep flight of stairs on the back of a hill and finally, finally make it.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Okay, number 6.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Yeah.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: 10 minutes late to Mariam’s front gate. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: Hello?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Hi! It's Svea. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: We walk up an open stairwell to the second floor, a long balcony reaches past other apartment doors. Mariam is standing in front of hers. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Hello, baby. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: Hi!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Hi. This is Jozefien.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Hi!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: Hi, Jozefien. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: I’m Jozefien.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: Hi, you too! Please, come in.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Thank you.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Thank you.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: We have a guest today.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Oh, hi! </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Mariam’s husband is sitting at a desk facing the wall immediately opposite the entry of their small two-bedroom apartment.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><em><strong>Matas:</strong></em> Hi, I’m Matas. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: His name is Matas. He works in the nonprofit sector here, but in Egypt he was a comedian.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Can I put my shoes here?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: Yes, you can do anything.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Okay. Oh my God, I love you place! It’s so cute. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Their place is brightly coloured with art on the walls. It's not new, but it's open concept, with a beautiful newly renovated kitchen on the right.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: it’s cute and tiny and very convenient, ‘cause everything is, like, within…</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Totally, totally! You see an accident happen and you’re like: “Wow!”. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: They have a sliding glass door onto a very small cinder-block lined patio. You can hear the freeway nearby.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Look, Jozefien!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Ooo, this is great! </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Mariam painted the walls of the yard space bright turquoise and it reflects a bluish light into the small living quarters. she's also gathered wood chips from the Berkeley city yard and created a playground-like space for her kids. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: I tried to make it convenient and accessible, but they rarely come and play here.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Mariam offers us some refreshments.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: Can I offer you some snacks? I can make you…</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: I'm okay.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: dandelion tea, which is this, like, really nice…</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: That sounds good. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">And, it is so good!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: These are my favourite, the turmeric and caramel nut. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Ooo, caramel nut sounds good. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: And, they’re nice with cream, so, just, if you don’t do dairy they won’t be nice. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: The lactose induced indigestion is totally worth taking.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: Yeah, for a while I wasn’t making anything, it was down the outlet I had to, like, decorate the house and tweak and tinker and play, so, that's why it’s, every corner has something.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: It’s really cool.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">She shows us a small corner where she does her drawings and paintings.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: This is where I work. Everything is very compressed and efficient and every, every little corner’s been utilised.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: There's a bright desk lamp, pegboard, almost all the way up the wall, and shelves above your head.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: As soon as you come into the house there’s a wall. On the left side I have a pegboard wall, has all our things from glue, staples, yarn, tape, everything you can possibly use to make something, drill some panels with drawings, envelopes, shoe rack, sewing stuff, you know, books. And, in the front you see shelves, it has lots of storage, books, paper, scraps, photos of us and printer and my desk and all the paints and my work. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Lots of light.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: One of the desk legs is covered in baby photos.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: Well, we have all the photos here for Taha, because when Karima, our youngest daughter, was born, he felt really left out, so, we had to, like, show him that he was here first, he's very much loved and all the people that love him, the grandparents, the aunts, the uncles, so, it’s only about him now, which has to change soon ‘cause she starts to understand what's going on. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: There’s a laptop stand on Mariam’s desk which she has angled so that it can be a height adjustable easel.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: I just got that ‘cause I was hunching over so much and hurting my back, so, it just raises up the the drawing. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">It’s kind of like an easel for the desk.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Artists, take note! This is a great idea.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">And, do you sit on this chair?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: Yeah. It just happened ‘cause we have that chair, it wasn’t really intentional. I like ‘cause it's big enough for my bum. I guess that's here for longer. I like working from home, I wouldn't do a studio ever because I, I would have to replicate everything in the studio and I don't want to do that, and I work at night while the kids are sleeping, so, it’s really convenient for me to have this work space be at home.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: I spy a quote, written on a card and stuck above Mariam’s desk.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: A quote?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: An inspirational saying. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: Oh, yeah, “I am enough”. Yeah, it’s, it's been a journey to get to here. I've, like, struggle, struggled with making art for the past 10 plus years because I just didn’t, I don't see many people that looked like me or artists, and I didn't see people who are normal, normal artists that weren’t like eccentric and depressive and, like, I’m just a normal person. I’m, like, from Egypt, you know.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: We set up in Mariam’s child’s room. We drape a blanket over the bed’s wooden frame, it's a pink blanket and as we cuddle inside it's like a three of us are preschoolers in our own homemade fort.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: No boys allowed! </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><i>music</i></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: I studied Fine Arts to begin with at American University of Cairo and then I transferred after two years, after finishing all my major requirements. I went to Pratt Institute in New York and studied interior design. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">After that, I went back to Egypt, worked for a year, a year and a half, in interior design stuff and got my soul sucked out of me. Meanwhile I was working on, I was writing poetry, even though I don't write any poetry now, and I wouldn't even consider it poetry, but just writing stories that were really important for me to share and I didn't find an outlet in Egypt at the time, so, I just decided to start an open mic and had my first open mic in 2009, that was pre-revolution, Egyptian Revolution, and it just spiralled out of there and we became the biggest travelling open, open mic event in Egypt. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">It's illegal to have groups of people come together in Egypt, like, you can't do that, we did that anyway in cafes and we somehow went under the radar and lots of people, like, found their voice through this movement. It was called ‘Mashrah i Marich’, which means the Mars project. It's one of these things that kind of took off even beyond my power, beyond my ability, like, I'm not a very charismatic person, but somehow, and I'm very shy, and somehow is MC’ing these events in front of hundreds and hundreds of people that didn't know, and we've had hundreds of open mic’s all over and it’s, it was, it was amazing. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">‘Cause it wouldn’t, we didn’t even have much of an underground music and art movement in Egypt but it kind of took off from there. So, before the revolution people were more metaphorical about what they wanted to say, things were more hidden, read between the lines kind of thing, and after was like: “Waaahh!”, everything was being said out in the open, like, like people were just like tongues out, mouth open, like. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">I think when you have more limitations you push to be more artistic, definitely, so after I feel like there was more ranting than artfullness and how good things were said, and after that, it balanced out again, people were trying to say something from their own self that was meaningful rather than just like running the first sprint.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><i>music</i></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: After five years of doing that I wasn't really having my own practice and it started to itch, like, I want to do something for myself and I just started to retract from the project. During that time I got married and it was, we were planning to move here to Oakland, so, there were a lot of identity changes for me, like, being married, moving. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">I had so many more layers to who I was as a first perception of me, like, brown, Arab, whatever, Muslim, all these things that I don't know people are getting, or reading or not. To walk in the world as someone who knows how people see her or sees her identity and knows exactly the negative connotations that are associated with that, that I have to, like, counter that constantly in my movements at the grocery store, walking into the store, being with my kids, I don't want to shout at them, so they’ll think I'm this kind of person, like, just everything I do I feel like I'm being watched. So, anyway, identity has been like a hovering thing for me ever since I moved to the US, which is almost five years ago.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><i>music</i></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: When I was pregnant I got really anxious ‘cause I didn't feel like I would have a place in the art world as a mom, ‘cause I don't see many moms and I was researching who’s, who's an artist as a mom and I stumbled upon this video of this one artist who was saying: “You can't be an artist if you’re mom, you can't make good art if you’re a mom”, and at the same time bombarded with this ideal vision of a mom and all this beauty and and glowiness and slenderness and all these, like, perfection driven imagery of mom, motherhood, that was all very unrealistic for me. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">At the beginning I was like: “Okay, when I'm a mom I'm going to feel this or when I'm pregnant I'm going to feel this glow or this beauty and I'm going to feel so good”, but I wasn't feeling so good, it was heavy and I, I didn't eat the things I wanted to eat and I couldn’t do things I wanted to do it, so, I wasn't feeling that like amazingness when I was pregnant and after that I was like: “I love my child but it was hard!”. I didn't see much of that struggle and I hear much of it, I felt like I was alone a lot of the time, because am I the only one struggling with this? Why are all the images so beautiful and perfect and powdery pink with like puppies on white carpets? </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">I'm like, there's this chaos in my life! And I feel like part of this project is receiving stories from mom’s. I put a a call for moms to send me their photos and I would illustrate it for them and part of that was reading their stories, it was so healing just to know that, wow, it's not just me, you know, even though I'm around lots of moms now and I do know that what I'm going through is normal, it's just to see that from all over the world mom’s are still, are struggling with the same issues and body image, you know, everyone has their unique perspective, but in a way it's also universal. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">It's really important represent this kind of motherhood, the real, the raw, the chaotic and in a beautiful way, through art. So, I think it's actually important for more of this to happen, more people to acknowledge this invisible motherhood energy that's in everyone's life whether they like it or not,’cause they're born from a mother, even if they don't have contact with their mother, even if they're not a mother they have mothers, you know mothers. So, you're in constant contact with motherhood, yet, I feel as a mother I was extremely invisible and my work was extremely invalued. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">I was always asked: “So, what do you do besides that?”, I'm like: “I can barely do that to begin with, I can barely do the whole motherhood thing to begin with”, there's so much expectation, yet no acknowledgement of effort, no the recognition, no credit. It's a very strange thing. It took me a such a long time to be like: “I’m a mom, yuck, I'm not young”. Now I’m like: “I’m a mom, it's okay”, I can also I'm whoever I am it doesn’t… </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">In a way the whole identity thing I was working with, struggling with, it got lifted, ‘cause now I don't care, I just want to live, I just want to have my my lunch, I just want to, like, make sure my kids are alive in the car seat buckled and then in their beds asleep. And everything else doesn't matter.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><i>music</i></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: The Motherhood Illustrated project, I feel like I'm exercising through it, exercising my skills, skill with materials and also my practice, like, how do I sit down and do things, like, just learning basics of how do I hold a brush again, how do I sit, like, discipline about that. So, in the beginning I was going to do line drawings, just the ink stuff, and and now I'm doing more watercolour and the watercolour is getting super detailed and is getting out of control for me and it’s taking me like a week, a week and a half for each one, it’s, it's taking way longer. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">I'm getting super sucked into the detail, I don't know if that's good or bad, but for now I'm like going crazy. It's been a big learning process with the technique of watercolour, I've been learning so much about it. You do it and then it settles however it wants to settle and that's also a very telling of motherhood, like, I want it to go this way, but it's going to go wherever it needs to go, it's going to settle, it doesn’t settle really, it's going to go where it needs to go and this lack of control is what motherhood has, has taught me so much, like, you do what you can, when you can, and most of the time you don't do what you want. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">The subjects I had were the things that layed around in my house, like, a vacuum cleaner, scrub brush. So, it started off, like, I’m not going to think about my subject, I'm just going to do what's in front of me. I was having so much fun! It was so fulfilling, so satisfying, so good to have something to do beyond the kids and the house and I think that led to the motherhood thing, because the most present function that's for me, as a person in this world is motherhood, I am mothering all the time, it's non-stop! </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">And, I remember, like, when I was pregnant, I had so much anxiety ‘cause I was hoping to move here and start my art career and like find myself and as soon as I came here I got pregnant. So, I was like: “Oh, no. Something’s going to take over, I don't know what it is, I don't know any mother artists”. I actually bought lots of mother, mother artist books that had stories in them and that really helped. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">It was kind of depressing though, because a lot of them would say: “We have, like, three hours to work a day”, and I’d be like: “What? I need like sixteen hours, what are you talking about?”, and I remember being in a studio a while ago and this mom would come from 9am to 3pm and I’d be like: “How do you ever do anything? How could you ever do anything in six hours? You're crazy, you're never going to get anywhere”, and now I'm like: “Oh, I have an hour! What?! That’s crazy!”, which I do, that's what I have in a day, really, with commuting, dropping off and rehabilitating myself after the morning chaos, it’s really like an hour, an hour and a half if I’m lucky and after they’re asleep when I have zero energy.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><i>music</i></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: What do you love about your studio?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: I like that it's in my house. I like that I can make tea in my breaks and pee and change my clothes and check on my kids and run to the store quickly then come back and not that being a big deal. I like the convenience of it.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: So do you paint when your kids are playing?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: They’ll never let me do that.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Yeah, you check on your kids.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: When they're sleeping, of course! Whenever I just, like, think about doing something or like </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">holding a brush my kid wants me to carry her. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Do they try to join you?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: I think so, I think so. Sometimes I, I make it a thing, I put Taha next to me and give him a piece of paper and paint and it works for like 10 minutes.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><i>music</i></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: In Egypt, in transition from open mic’ing into designing and doing things, it was actually in a very interesting place called, ‘Dar Bersabad Sabad A Montoshar’, it’s a potter’s community and it’s originally a poor area. A bunch of artist came together and set up an art gallery there and my friend has a studio there and I would come, I would go work with her. It's a, it's very, it's a very interesting space. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">I don't think there's many artist communities, but the ones that are there are really interesting and multi, multi-class. You know how, like, there's racial stuff here, there’s class issues in Egypt, so, to have a multi-class complex is kind of a rarity. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">So, it was, it's nice to work side by side with people who have different backgrounds than you and to learn from them, because most of them don’t go to school or don't continue school, so, they have actually a much better grasp of their skill than most people who go to school because they practice more. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Things are changing in Egypt, like, this is a bigger conversation, but people that I grew up with are very much trying to distance themselves from religion. So, they're actually trying to represent themselves more as Westerners, so you wouldn't actually know the difference, except from the, how they look from their skin, but generally people in Egypt are very modest, very conservative,… Actually, they look more modest than they are, because it's a cultural norm to cover your hair and, and younger people tend to just like dress more tight, most girls cover their hair even though they wouldn't if they traveled. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">People have, I would say, moved away from it being a religious thing to a social thing. I actually started wearing a head covering like five years ago. I wasn’t, I didn’t grow up with it, no one in my family do it, my social circle disapproves, actually, of it, because it does represent that conservative dark uneducated aspect of religion, but for me it was, it was a calling and I don't know exactly the source and it was very hard for me to come out, actually. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">I feel like I haven't actually come out, because I don't want to get questioned, because I feel like it was such a cerebral decision, it was, not cerebral, a visceral decision, like, I don't actually know why, but this, eventually I’ll know why, ‘cause I, if there's one thing I knew I wasn’t going to do, it was to cover my hair, never. And then it just happened and it's been, like, a very difficult and amazing at the same time, like, it's very difficult to walk with an identity, and it is difficult in Egypt in my social circles and it's also difficult here because suddenly I’m, I represent so much more than who I am. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">People that expect me to be ignorant or violent or whatever the news is saying these days, right, I feel like I have to<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>disprove people all the time. I am extra smiley sometimes, like, I try to speak to my kids in English in a very sweet tone, even though I don't always want to be sweet with them, you know, I’m a normal person. I want to scream at them sometimes. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><i>music</i></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: I love my religion, I love everything is brings, the more I learn about it, the more I just feel so comfortable having guidelines and having healing guides and knowing that everything is actually normal, everything I'm going through is normal and that there are ways to deal with this.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: So, the covering wasn’t a religious thing? </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: It was.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: It was.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: It was, it was, it was a religious decision and that was the hardest part of it. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: A visceral, religious decision. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: Yeah. And, it's been great for me. It’s, it's been, like I said, difficult, because it's like that identity part and I've always seen myself as beautiful and people have always complimented my looks, my face, my hair, my body, I consider them still beautiful, but suddenly, like, it's not accessible and I'm not being affirmed in the world in a way like, I had to tell Matas: “You know, you have to tell me I'm beautiful way more now, because I'm not getting that”.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><i>music</i></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>mq</i></strong>: My email is melquessny: m e l q u e s s n y, at gmail.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><i>music</i></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: And welcome back from Mariam Quessny’s kid’s bedroom. I'm so glad that you could join us.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: It was very soft and fluffy</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: It was so soft and fluffy, it was really awesome girl time! I had so much fun talking to her. I know you're so sad to see us go, but the time is running out on our show today. Jozefien, who do we have a crush on next?</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: Next episode, we have a crush on Elle Sofe Sara.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>sv: </strong>Elle Sofe Sara is an incredible choreographer; she’s also an Indigenous woman and a reindeer herder here in Sápmi, the European Arctic. You can follow her on Instagram at ellesofe, all one word. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>jb:</strong> get ready!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: My name is Svea Vikander.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: And, I'm Jozefien Buydens.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Please remember to subscribe, rate, and review. We’re new here.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>jb</i></strong>: See you next time!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>sv</i></strong>: Bye!</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><i>outro music</i></span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Transcription of &quot;What Tramaine de Senna Thinks about Rhinestones&quot;</title>
        <author>
            <name>ART CRUSH INTERNATIONAL</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://artcrushinternational.com/transcription-tramaine.html"/>
        <id>https://artcrushinternational.com/transcription-tramaine.html</id>

        <updated>2021-03-30T11:30:53+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    jb: Hello hello and welcome to a new episode of Art Crush&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <div><strong>jb</strong>: Hello hello and welcome to a new episode of Art Crush International. I'm Jozefien Buydens</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>sv:</strong> I'm Svea Vikander</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> And together we take you into the artist studios of the world. Because these artist studios are just wonderful places with lots of light, beautiful artworks, comfy chairs, and lots more. Svea, where are we going?</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>sv:</strong> Today we're going to Antwerp</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> In Belgium!</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>sv:</strong> That's right. Have you heard of this place called Belgium?</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Uh, yes. I have heard of the place called Belgium because I'm Belgian, I was born there, I grew up there.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>sv:</strong> Yeah it's a really nice place you should go there sometime. But today we are going to visit the studio of Tramaine de Senna</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> That's so exciting, can you tell us a bit more?</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>sv:</strong> Tramaine, Tramaine de Senna is your friend,</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> It's my friend, it's true, but you can introduce her!</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>sv:</strong> I'll talk about her, yeah. So your friend Tramaine de Senna, who lives in your country, Belgium, also has roots in the Bay Area and she's a visual artist. She does sculpture and textile work. And you can find her on Instagram at @tramainedesenna. [spells out] And yeah, she's really wonderful and she has a studio in Antwerp and she can also talk about her experiences in the Bay Area as well. So we're gonna get a really interesting compare and contrast today.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> I've been really looking forward to doing this interview with Tramaine so, we'll have a blast.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>sv:</strong> That's right</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Ok</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>sv:</strong> The ceiling can't hold us</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> No, they can't, they can't. Shall we hop on a plane, to see Tramaine?</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>sv:</strong> Let's go!</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> I'm Tramaine de Senna, an artist living in Antwerp, Belgium. But I'm proudly from Vallejo California.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> I drive the car to Tramaine's studio, which is located in Deurne, one of Antwerp's suburbs. Even though I only need to drive for 35 km, it takes me almost 2 hours to get there. As everyone in Belgium knows, Antwerp has a huge traffic problem. So I should have seen this coming. I park the car in the parking lot and go look for Tramaine.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>There are a few studio spaces on the property, as well as a beer cellar. Two employees are standing outside the shop looking at me suspiciously. I can see them thinking Who is this woman and why oh why is she carrying around a huge old fashioned cell phone with a fluffy hat. Note: the old fashioned cell phone? That's my recorder. And the fluffy thing on top? That's the windshield. So I don't catch loud windy noises when recording outside.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>I feel like I'm being watched so I smile, nod to say hello and keep on looking. When I can't find the entrance to Tramaine's studio, I give her a call.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> (over the phone): this is Tramaine!</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Hi Tramaine, this is Jozefien. Um, I'm here.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> Hi, I'm gonna come right down and find ya.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> OK perfect, see you soon!</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Oh, hi hi!</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> Where'd you park?</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Oh right there, is that alright?</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> Yeah yeah yeah, nice to see you!</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Oh yeah, nice to see you again, too.</div>
<div>We walk up the stairs to the first floor and enter Tramaine's spacious studio on the right.</div>
<div>wow, my god this is a big space.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> I think we're lucky. Because I don't think all the spaces have this kind of light, ceiling.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Oh yeah yeah yeah, yeah that's good. How do you call it in English? Lichtkoepels?</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> Skylight! I'll show you what we have.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Before we drive into our studio tour, Tramaine offers to cook us delicious quesadillas because it's already after lunch time.</div>
<div>You're so sweet. I'm here to interview you and I'm getting food instead.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> But isn't that what artist studios are like,</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> consequently, we cozily chat our way through the afternoon and almost forget we have an interview to do! Let's get to work!</div>
<div>Well mostly we start at around 10 and then it's finished around noon.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> Oh my. You can start, I'm just gonna like cook these while I'm...</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> No, that's alright.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>[music]</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> This is the studio,</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> yay!</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> Thanks for coming</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> sure, thanks for showing me around</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> Yeah you're welcome Like, I have a lot of art stored against the wall here</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> we're looking [duck down more] at some wrapped artworks on the right when entering Tramaine's studio</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> very large sculptures, large wooden panels and frames from other artworks. I think we're gonna throw away some stuff.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Oh, really</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> Yeah, and there's also paintings from other people, too. So that's nice.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Moving forward, we arrive at the first of many of Tramaine's work stations.</div>
<div><strong> </strong></div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> tools and a machine for drying paint which is pretty handy and a—</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Which one?</div>
<div><strong> </strong></div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> This one, it's pretty handy, yeah yeah, it's great. It's something that you need for a studio but if you're at home it would eat up your electricity, you know? It's very practical. That's a band saw and I remember at Berkeley when I was there, there was a picture of a bloody finger detached with a little string in between it, like some kind of organ because it was like, "Do not,—watch your fingers."</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Important</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> Yeah very much so. So that thing can take stuff off. So, next to the tool box just like a large work table with a lot of junk on it right now.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> So this is the spot where you work?</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> actually I work across from it, I have more tables</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Oh wow wow wow</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> yeah, different media. So this is like, crushing things or painting stuff. This table, taking things apart, yeah you see a whole bike chain. I gotta clean it up. Yeah.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>[music]</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> But also a small kitchenette because when you're working for a while or if you need to make glue out of flour salt and water, it's handy to have a hot plate. The studio came with the refrigerator and microwave too, so it's a pretty handy thing when you wanna put in long hours, it's nice to feel comfy actually. So yeah that's what you see and next to all of that is plenty of book supplies, just tools.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Yeah, it looks very organized.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> Yes! You know you need a little bit of organization so you can cut loose with making art.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Do you wanna show your other work table?</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> Yes, so a little turn, this is another table that I use for fabrics, fabric work , sewing, maybe painting small objects. It's like a dry table. And it has cardboard on it right now because cardboard is really great, accessible, I can find it on the street but it's just a really great surface to work on if it's clean. So I'll just put out a cloth and then I'll do ironing and stuff, for working with fabrics that cannot get dirty. It's always this spot. This spot is always a very clean spot, you can make objects and keep it kind of pristine.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> And there's a huge jar with colourful beads.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> Yes, yeah, um, it's great to look at. I haven't incorporated it in my art yet. Oh wait actually I made a little art piece on the wall with some of these rhinestones but um, I really enjoy some of these colour combinations because they remind me of toys from when I was a kid. Barbie and the Rockers, Barbie had her own rock group...</div>
<div> </div>
<div>When I look at her clothing or her tools, little guitars and stuff, they had really great colour texture fabric combinations. For instance like a neon green with a magenta and maybe some yellow in there. So with some of these rhinestones I bought them just to have fun with it, and can I show you over here?</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Tramaine takes me to another work station on our left to show me one of her artworks.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> So I made this 3D card. There's actually a second one out there that I gave to my lawyer. But I use the rhinestones to accentuate this card which is Jambie the Genie and Jambie is a character on Pee Wee's playhouse, a great TV show for children which came out in 1987 and it went until 1991 but um I love the character Genie because it's the only character on the show which is not an animal come to life or a piece of furniture that has come to life.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>It's its own thing, something supernatural. And it's really great to think of this thing, this entity that allows you to make wishes and maybe they can come true. The whole show is imaginative and creative. But this one character is just -- it kind of looks creepy, the card I made, the rhinestones but it's also a little surprising reminder.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> and it's very sweet. and the head turns around</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> yeah the head can turn but maybe one day I can make it into a brooch somehow. But yeah, that's jambie's head because it's a head in a box and when you say something like 'wish' the box opens and then he starts talking.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> And there is also this golden shelf</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> The golden shelf?</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> No, the golden shell, the golden shell</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> The golden shell, yes, a girl friend of mine who's also an artist, a painter, gave this to me at the opening of the last show I had, "Supernatural" in Antwerp. She got it at a vending machine, it had a toy in it but I guess she gave it to me because the chair objects I made for the show reminder her of this scallop!</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Oh, I can see that</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> Yeah yeah, I love it actually I love scallops because it's like the little mermaid—Ok, all these things going back to toys, I'm revealing all my influences but that's okay.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Toys, that's important</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> yeah yeah</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Oh and this, there's another desk in the corner?</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> Yeah, there's a lot. But which one should I tell you about? Like this is the boring one, that's the exciting one.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Let's go to the exciting one.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>On the wall in front of us, hangs Tramaine's collection of photographs that serve as her inspiration</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> I'm sure everyone collects images, or things that intrigue them somehow. I remember doing that in high school but also at Berkeley in my architecture studio but even now I still collect images. I hang them up above the wall to think about stuff. And they actually influence me to make objects.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>But what I find, I would like to transfer the aura that these images have into an object. And that's, that's kind of like the first parts of making art for me. So yeah, it's uh, I just collect theses things that alternate between civilization, these monuments of civilizations and also home decor, or cozy things, or movie sets, or objects or toys.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> It's nice!</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> Thank you.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Do the pictures change over time?</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> Some pictures I add to and some I take out but then some I keep with me for a long time. Also, images from the Wizard of Oz I've been keeping with me for the past 8 years also. Because my father likes that film, it's an influence for people but also just aesthetic-wise, it's beautiful, it's monumental, it's made in the late '30s, and the character Dorothy going on a journey, which people can relate to, going on a journey whether it's physical or not.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>But her being surrounded by these three characters -- these male characters -- but they're actually symbolically different facets of her, you know? But in order to show a multiplicity of being the storyteller shows it in different characters. So I really like the idea of a journey somehow and the mystery within people.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>And then, yeah, new images come in. But roughly throughout the years, I've paid attention to my archives and they just basically stay the same. And they're images that either I've taken or that I've found, took photos of, or things that I've found online too. It comes, they come back to life. Where they're being reprinted again or scanned, or printed again, or living in my computer. And then again, we have some toys here also</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Oh yeah, here he is, right?</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> Isn't that amazing? Because my auntie, whenever my sister and I would visit her house with my uncle, she had all these tchotchkes in her cabinet and one of them, she would have all these toys from PeeWee's playhouse and you couldn't touch them but you could look at em, so it was like amazing, I'm sure when I go to see her she will still have those toys and I'll stare at them.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Now that the studio tour is done, we set up at the kitchen table to continue our interview.</div>
<div>What do you like about the studio space you're in now?</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> Oh my gosh what do I like about it? I love the fact that there is light coming in from the ceiling and you and I were talking about that. Like um, skylights? But I forgot how you say that in Netherlands?</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Lichtkoepels </div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> [repeats] That's what i love about it. And I've always wanted that, in the back of my mind wherever I've gone. I've always wanted to have really great natural light somehow. So I am very lucky to have this studio with <em>lichtkoepels</em> in the ceiling. So I like that and I like the fact that there are other people here, in this building. Other artists as well.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>When I open the windows I can hear them, which is cool. But also when I open the windows there are all these, there are many rooftops that I can see. And it's kind of like in the back lot of the streets so you have—it's funny how things are set up over here in Belgium. You have the facade of houses and the entrance way of houses and stuff. But when you look closely between spaces you can see that there might be interior courtyards. Or maybe in this courtyard there's a supermarket.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>But in this case there's also this back story of how people live. You see the interiors of people's houses. Not here but in other spaces. But one of these days what I'd like to do when I open these windows is to actually build a physical bridge -- it's a maybe 6 foot span to the next rooftop. And my neighbours can easily go onto these rooftops but for me there is corrugated clear roofing that shows what is underneath, which is like a beer cellar. So there is no way that I can climb onto this roof and jump onto the other roof.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>Then when I don't make art I can sunbathe! In the privacy of not many people seeing me, which is great.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> If there was one thing you could change about the studio, what would it be?</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> good question! I would raise the roof, like uh, make the ceiling higher. Which is impossible because this is all poured-in-place concrete. But having high ceilings is so nice, it's just a nice feeling. And it's really hard to find. You can find it in fancy chic buildings but not in studios so much. But when you do it's really great, it's a great feeling.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> would you store more?</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> [chuckles] Yeah I know, huh. And that becomes an excuse to store more crap and art! Yes Josie, thank you [laughter], yes I would collect more things to store, yeah yeah. Yeah maybe, build higher shelves and store things, I guess. Yeah.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>[music]</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> The first thing, as a child you start off creating things and for me I just enjoyed it and it just stuck. And all throughout my schooling my classmates always encouraged me and my teachers did too. And my father was always concerned because he has this idea that artists always make money when they're dead which yeah, it happens! My mom always supported me as well.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>My dad was wanting me to be more well-rounded so when I went off to college that, you know, it's this kind of immigrant idea that you must  work hard, study hard, and go to university to get a good job so you can support your family. So I followed through with architecture but I also studied art and I went into architecture but I always wanted to make art, and I always did, but there was one person my dad knew.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>It was the mother of his friend named Nancy, [name]. And she was the first person I ever met who was extremely cultured. She passed away a few years ago. She would have been maybe 80 now. She married a doctor and then eventually, she was also married to a lawyer, but she lived in San Francisco on Divisadero, and her neighbour below her was former governor Jerry Brown, you know what I mean? She was super high class.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>But she, I don't know, she liked my sister and I. She introduced us to SF MOMA when we were kids. I mean, I remember she took us there and I saw Jeff Koons' Michael Jackson With Bubbles statue, and I think it was an exhibition, the main exhibition there was about drawings from kids who were abused, sexually abused, and I remember seeing her cry. And I never saw Nancy cry or be so emotional but that was pretty cool to see someone cry, viewing artwork, especially someone like her.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>But she was quite a figure for me. And my mom always gave my sister and I play dough and whenever we would visit my mom we were always making stuff or sewing things. So it's just always stayed and it's just been a path of how to find my way so I can make art. You gotta do all these other things, you gotta go to school for other stuff and take jobs or whatever. But the main thing is always because I need to make art. I need to go this way because I have to make art.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>[music]</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> You went to art school from university onward or were you also in art school in high school?</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> In high school we had art classes and stuff but I went to the University of California at Berkeley and so I did a simultaneous degree, I studied architecture but I was also in art. The silly thing was because I was in both programs, I couldn't identify with either one and I always thought well, I will never be an artist but I'll just make stuff. I didn't know how to dream.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>But then afterwards when I got out and got these desk jobs, I really wanted to pursue art but I just thought I couldn't because there was no way to make a living. I worked for about seven years, working in various jobs. And I had enough money saved up to go back to school. I wanted to go to art school but I couldn't do it in the States because for me it was just a little bit too expensive at the time, and I also wanted to get out of the country for a bit just to see what was going on outside the Bay Area.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>I was trying to become fluent in German for the longest time, so I could go to art school in Germany because I had exposure to Germany for a while and I really liked their schooling and the people who were there, it just—the price of food and transportation and all that stuff was really nice, and kind of modest. I was in Berlin in 2009 and I met some Dutch artists. And at that time I had finished my job at a magazine and I had applied for a residency because I was thinking, "Well why not," you know? "I need to try it." So I found a residency in Berlin.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>And I met an artist duo and some of their friends and I thought, "OK, they came from the Netherlands. Where is this country? And how did it produce such quirky and amazing artists?!" So I decided yeah, I should go to the Netherlands for art school and it turns out they had programs in English as well. I studied at Sintyos (?) this was in Brega (?) in Surtoganbox (?) that's in the South of the Netherlands.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>So I got my Master's there and right after I was accepted into an art institute in Belgium. In Ghent, the Hogha (?) Institute for KjonKunsten (?) Which was actually part of a two year program where they actually, they give you a studio and you have access to people in the art world, mostly in Belgium, other artists or curators, or directors and stuff. So after the [HISL?] I didn't know whether to stay in Belgium or to go back to America and I actually did go back to America but some stuff happened so for now I'm still in Belgium. I'm in Antwerp now.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>[music]</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> I guess I also wanna ask: how has moving to Europe changed y9our art practice? And if so, how did it change it?</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> That's a good question. When I look back at my body of work, the work I've produced, it was always kind of changing. Because I was trying to experiment with different media and usually the thoughts were always the same. But I chose to come to Western Europe because I needed that space of reflection somehow. Just to not only think about who I am or the country I came from, but just space.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>I had this Euro-centric idea when I was in the States that I have to go to Western Europe because they must know their stuff. You have the Italians with the high renaissance, or the basic architecture or art history, or even architecture history classes I took at Berkeley always revolved around Western Europe somehow. I mean, it did kind of touch up on the Asias and the Middle east, and a little bit on Africa, not much about South America at all, but it was really Euro-centric.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>So I thought "OK, that must be where I should go. They must know better somehow." It's funny because even without trying, when I meet people they say, "Ah, your art looks very American or very Californian because there's so much colour in it."</div>
<div> </div>
<div>And um, how has my art changed? Hmmm it just always continues to change. I think if anything, I still, my mind is still in America. Even when I was getting critiqued over here, a lot of the issues I was trying to examine were American issues. So it was kind of hard to get feedback because there aren't many Americans or people from the Americas to give me feedback that I needed at times. But also that's fine because it's something larger.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>For a while I wanted to examine my own problems or things I was wondering about. I examined ti in my art but also after a while, it was like, it's kinda. it's boring, I'm not actually interested in it because if I were someone else I wouldn't be interested in it, if that makes sense. Because everyone has a story, but the story doesn't always have to be heard, you know? So sometimes I think, "Ah yeah, my story, actually, pshhh, if I was someone else I wouldn't wanna hear it."</div>
<div> </div>
<div>What really makes me interested in other humans is how they maintain their humanity, how they overcome things. But how they do it in their own exuberant way. Because for instance—I'll make it quick—there's this guy named CorlaPandit, and he was this supposedly really exotic piano player who had televised television broadcasts of him playing piano on TV in the '50s, I think. But it turns out this guy, CorlaPandit, who had a head wrap and a jewel on his forehead, he said he came from somewhere in India, at that time, it was accepted in America because like, "Oh this exotic guy, who knows where India is?" I mean, people weren't used to it.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>So he introduced to this large audience, mostly homemakers at home in the afternoon, he showed them this exotica music. He maintained this practice until the passed away. He was even in the Ted Burton film Ed Wood. But it turns out CorlaPandit wasn't Indian! He totally falsified this. Him and his wife, she was a worker for Disney, they made this persona up for him to get jobs. He was actually a Black man! Um, somewhere from Missouri or something. Roland....Brown or something? Red, reed, Brown?</div>
<div> </div>
<div>He adapted this persona because as a black man in the US, there was this thing called the one drop rule: if you had any drop of Black blood you would be considered Black, even though you might have blond hair and blue eyes, if you have any Black history, then you, there could be ways to discriminate against you. So when this guy went from Missouri to Hollywood, he could not play as a Black man. So he changed his name to like, Juan Rolando, to be a Latino, so he can at least join a union and play music and have gigs and make money.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>But eventually, him and his wife, they made this persona. And as an Indian man, he was able to show his talent. And I think that's just like a really amazing story. I mean not only was he talented but he found a way to go through a system. And it could also be a little bit offensive because yeah, it's offensive to people who are Indians. But I think yeah, that's a great story. He went through oppression but he found his way around it. So I find these stories amazing. So many things inspire me, too. But yeah, being in Western Europe, how does it change my artwork? I also learned that, for me it was like finding out how do people operate, which is the same anywhere. But like, are people funded by the government, do they get grants, or are they represented by galleries, or do they open their own spaces? Like how do people exist as artists. And I was curious because there seemed to be a very accessible, quick artist community in the places that I've been able to live here. In the Netherlands and in Belgium, somehow.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> So you found your art community pretty fast?</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> Well, um, it took a while. But like when you know someone and they accept you, you join other communities. Or you meet a nice person. A lot of big things that have happened to me have been through other women artists or women curators and stuff like that. But I guess my point is that for me when I was in the States, I dunno, somehow I didn't know, I couldn't understand how the art world worked.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>The art world isn't just like the commercial, capitalistic side. There's all these other things, too. But I didn't know how it operated, I didn't know who did it or how it ran, or how museums ran, you know, if you show your stuff there, they're not responsible for sales and all that stuff. So just going over to Western Europe it was just really quick for me to like—OK, yeah, some artists are really great at selling themselves and they can live that way. But it's a small percentage. You have to earn a lot of money and half of it goes to taxes. So how do other artists do it? Some of them become teachers. But it's, it's everywhere and stuff. But it seemed more accessible. Like, I could find out quicker how it works. I'm still learning, so.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> You mentioned earlier that your mind is still in America?</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> Yeah, at times, yeah, unfortunately, yeah. In America sometimes but like actually it's also here. But a lot of the things I was trying to figure out because of my family's history, of them migrating around the world because of economic reasons, for hundreds of years. My dad comes from China, from Shanghai, but he's, Chinese, but part Portuguese and Dutch because of trade, of course. When you think about it, it's like, Yeah, China was opened up. And through religion and trade. So you have the Dutch also going over there. I mean, what explains my father's grandmother having red hair? Red haired woman in China? But yeah, it was actually a very cosmopolitan place.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>My mom's side is mostly descended from African slaves, with Native American blood. And my mom's father was half English and stuff. So for me it was always difficult: how do I make sense of this for myself? Because what culture do you identify with, somehow? We're American but we're also all these other types of people. And I was trying to figure that out in art. But I didn't want to ever draw a line and say, "I'm gonna make art about my Black experience" or whatever, because there actually was none. It's a mixture of everything.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>And the reason why I didn't wanna draw a line in anything and [I] focus more on objects—and objecthood—is because as soon as you say that you are this, then you, it's defining yourself based on what someone else is not. And sometimes that's very exclusive, it excludes other people. So for me I'd rather not really say it but just examine this through objects.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>That's how we all exist. I mean, we're surrounded by things that humans make or that occurs naturally. But we have relations with objects, also. And for a while, I used to think that it's really interesting to look at forms because there's all these histories within it. And with humans also our behavior in a way is a form. It kind of shows where you're coming from somehow, how you are. Or your mental state.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>[music]</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> My father, along with his parents, he emigrated. And this is interesting as well, because a lot of us kids, the third generation, we're all doing creative things. And it's something that John Adams, who was a former President, he wrote to his wife Abigail Adams, "I must study warfare in order for my sons to study, like naval architecture and engineering, in order for their sons to study tapestry and painting." And, um, sewing and all that stuff.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>It takes three generations finally to crawl out of poverty or to assimilate into another land, and to allow for your grandchildren to make art. To get to the point. Because someone has to crawl out of poverty, someone has to make money and get an education and then finally you're free, the next generation can make stuff. To think, to be able to have that time to think, and then make stuff.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>[music]</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> And actually on my mom's side, her father, he considered himself "Coloured" but he was born in England to his English mother, who had red hair, and to a, his Black father. Who came from West Virginia, which was Fayetteville, a coal mining town. That man, my great grandpa, Alfonso Pierce, did not want to work in the coal mines, as a Black man. Or as any man! You don't want to work in the coal mines, it's terrible work, and terrible health effects.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>So he went up to Ohio and this is around the turn of the century, the 1900s, to get an education and he decided to jump on a ship and he fled to England where he met my great-grandma. They got married, they had a kid (my grandpa) then they emigrated 1926 to New York, to Manhattan and they lived there and stuff, actually. But it was very difficult because there was the crash of '29 but with Alfonso, I actually googled his name and I found him.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>He actually had a patent on making a toy in the '50s and it was really cool! It was like this little rubber band feather contraption that if you pull something it'll fly. But it was so cool to see something from my great-grandfather, still alive, in a US patent, I don't know, system. He was applying for a patent for this toy. Yeah yeah yeah.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> it's beautiful. Your fascination for toys comes back!</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> Yeah, I didn't think of that! You drew a conclusion very quickly, Josie. Thank you very much!</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Well I'm not sure if you agree with it. [laughter]</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>tds:</strong> I didn't think of that somehow. Yeah yeah yeah, it's very nice!</div>
<div> </div>
<div>[music]</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Thanks for joining me on our visit with Tramaine in Antwerp. Remember you can see her work on our website, and you can follow Tramaine on Instagram. Because this episode was, yeah, not only travel to Belgium but also travel through time. And she's been up to some interesting things lately.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>sv:</strong> Indeed.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Thanks for listening to our show.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>sv:</strong> It means the world to me.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Who do we have a crush on in our next episode?</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>sv:</strong> In our next episode we have a crush on David Wilson. He has a website: <a href="http://davidwilsonandribbons.com/">davidwilsonandribbons.com</a>. But he's not on Instagram. And he also does not have a cell phone. But he's amazing and you can see some work by him on our website.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Speaking of, that's also where you can sign up for our newsletter. You'll get some special perk for signing up for it. But we don't know what yet.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>sv:</strong> Kisses? Like maybe kisses, air kisses through the air, like [kissing sounds]</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Absolutely! Until then, remember to rate and review and subscribe and just generally be nice to us and yourself and everyone.</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>sv:</strong> And follow us on Instagram at artcrush_international</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>jb:</strong> Love you!</div>
<div> </div>
<div><strong>sv:</strong> Bye!</div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Newsletter</title>
        <author>
            <name>ART CRUSH INTERNATIONAL</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://artcrushinternational.com/newsletter.html"/>
        <id>https://artcrushinternational.com/newsletter.html</id>

        <updated>2021-03-22T12:14:35+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Secret crushes and behind the scenes footage in our newsletter... * indicates required&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <!-- Begin Mailchimp Signup Form -->
<div id="mc_embed_signup"><form id="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" class="validate" action="https://artcrushinternational.us1.list-manage.com/subscribe/post?u=a5c4d920618c0fdc5f20955c6&amp;id=b8df586896" method="post" name="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" novalidate="" target="_blank">
<div id="mc_embed_signup_scroll">
<h2>Secret crushes and behind the scenes footage in our newsletter... </h2>
<div class="indicates-required"><span class="asterisk">*</span> indicates required<br><br></div>
<div class="mc-field-group"><label for="mce-EMAIL">Email Address <span class="asterisk">*</span> <br></label> <input id="mce-EMAIL" class="required email" name="EMAIL" required="" type="email" value=""><br><br></div>
<div class="mc-field-group"><label for="mce-FNAME">First Name <br></label> <input id="mce-FNAME" class="" name="FNAME" type="text" value=""><br><br></div>
<div class="mc-field-group"><label for="mce-LNAME">Last Name </label> <br><input id="mce-LNAME" class="" name="LNAME" type="text" value=""><br><br></div>
<div id="mce-responses" class="clear">
<div id="mce-error-response" class="response" style="display: none;"> </div>
<div id="mce-success-response" class="response" style="display: none;"> </div>
</div>
<!-- real people should not fill this in and expect good things - do not remove this or risk form bot signups-->
<div style="position: absolute; left: -5000px;" aria-hidden="true"><input tabindex="-1" name="b_a5c4d920618c0fdc5f20955c6_b8df586896" type="text" value=""></div>
<div class="clear"><input id="mc-embedded-subscribe" class="button" name="subscribe" type="submit" value="Subscribe"></div>
</div>
</form></div>
<p>
<script type="text/javascript" src="//s3.amazonaws.com/downloads.mailchimp.com/js/mc-validate.js"></script>
<script type="text/javascript">(function($) {window.fnames = new Array(); window.ftypes = new Array();fnames[0]='EMAIL';ftypes[0]='email';fnames[1]='FNAME';ftypes[1]='text';fnames[2]='LNAME';ftypes[2]='text';fnames[3]='ADDRESS';ftypes[3]='address';fnames[4]='PHONE';ftypes[4]='phone';fnames[5]='BIRTHDAY';ftypes[5]='birthday';}(jQuery));var $mcj = jQuery.noConflict(true);</script>
</p>
<!--End mc_embed_signup-->
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>What Tramaine de Senna Thinks About Rhinestones</title>
        <author>
            <name>ART CRUSH INTERNATIONAL</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://artcrushinternational.com/tramaine-de-senna.html"/>
        <id>https://artcrushinternational.com/tramaine-de-senna.html</id>

        <updated>2021-03-30T22:02:30+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://artcrushinternational.com/media/posts/10/big_candycoloredclown.jpg" alt="" />
                    We’re on our way to Belgium! Come eat quesadillas in Tramaine de&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://artcrushinternational.com/media/posts/10/big_candycoloredclown.jpg" alt="" />
                <p>We’re on our way to Belgium! Come eat quesadillas in Tramaine de Senna’s studio with us. She’s a mixed media artist with a background in architecture, proudly from Vallejo, California. Nowadays, she loves the light and space in the Antwerp studio she shares with her husband. It has a band saw and a paint dryer and a sewing machine and a huge jar of beads that’s great for looking at. De Senna talks love, absurdity, and the migration of forms. We can’t bring ourselves to leave.</p>
<p><strong>Some helpful vocabulary &amp; information:<br></strong>Lichtkoepels - the Dutch word for "skylights" <br>Korla Pandit - born John Roland Redd, known as a French-Indian musician from New Dehli, India. He lived and played music in the USA in the 1950s<br><span style="color: var(--text-editor-body-color); font-family: var(--font-base); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">Jambi, the genie - one of the characters of the television show Pee-wee's Playhouse <br></span><span style="color: var(--text-editor-body-color); font-family: var(--font-base); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);"><strong>European art schools Tramaine studied at:</strong><br></span><span style="color: var(--text-editor-body-color); font-family: var(--font-base); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">Sint-Joost School of Art &amp; Design, Breda, the Netherlands<br></span>HISK (Hoger Instituut voor Schone Kunsten), Ghent, Belgium</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-columns="3">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://artcrushinternational.com/media/posts/10/gallery/img_1838-1.jpg" data-size="2048x1536"><img loading="lazy" src="https://artcrushinternational.com/media/posts/10/gallery/img_1838-1-thumbnail.jpg" alt="" width="768" height="576"></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://artcrushinternational.com/media/posts/10/gallery/IMG_1840.JPG" data-size="4032x3024"><img loading="lazy" src="https://artcrushinternational.com/media/posts/10/gallery/IMG_1840-thumbnail.JPG" alt="" width="768" height="576"></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://artcrushinternational.com/media/posts/10/gallery/IMG_1846.JPG" data-size="4032x3024"><img loading="lazy" src="https://artcrushinternational.com/media/posts/10/gallery/IMG_1846-thumbnail.JPG" alt="" width="768" height="576"></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://artcrushinternational.com/media/posts/10/gallery/IMG_1849.JPG" data-size="4032x3024"><img loading="lazy" src="https://artcrushinternational.com/media/posts/10/gallery/IMG_1849-thumbnail.JPG" alt="" width="768" height="576"></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://artcrushinternational.com/media/posts/10/gallery/IMG_1851.JPG" data-size="4032x3024"><img loading="lazy" src="https://artcrushinternational.com/media/posts/10/gallery/IMG_1851-thumbnail.JPG" alt="" width="768" height="576"></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://artcrushinternational.com/media/posts/10/gallery/IMG_1856.JPG" data-size="1280x960"><img loading="lazy" src="https://artcrushinternational.com/media/posts/10/gallery/IMG_1856-thumbnail.JPG" alt="" width="768" height="576"></a></figure>
</div></div>
<p>Tramaine on Instagram: <a href="https://www.instagram.com/tramainedesenna/" class="">https://www.instagram.com/tramainedesenna/</a><br class="">Tramaine’s website: <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/tramainedesennamfa/" class="">https://sites.google.com/site/tramainedesennamfa/</a></p>
<p><a href="https://artcrushinternational.com/transcription-tramaine.html">Read the full transcript of Tramaine's interview here.</a> </p>
<div class="post__iframe"><iframe loading="lazy" width="400px" height="102px" src="https://anchor.fm/art-crush-international/embed/episodes/What-Tramaine-de-Senna-Thinks-About-Rhinestones-et6gak" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
